<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An excellent treatise teaching howe to cure the French-pockes with all other diseases arising and growing thereof, and in a manner all other sicknesses. Dravvne out of the bookes of that learned doctor and prince of phisitians, Theophrastus Paracelsus. Compiled by the learned Phillippus Hermanus, phisition and chirurgion. And now put into English by Iohn Hester in the spagiricall arte, practitioner.</title>
            <author>Paracelsus, 1493-1541.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03089</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108576</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844234</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844234</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9025</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03089)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9025)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 547:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An excellent treatise teaching howe to cure the French-pockes with all other diseases arising and growing thereof, and in a manner all other sicknesses. Dravvne out of the bookes of that learned doctor and prince of phisitians, Theophrastus Paracelsus. Compiled by the learned Phillippus Hermanus, phisition and chirurgion. And now put into English by Iohn Hester in the spagiricall arte, practitioner.</title>
                  <author>Paracelsus, 1493-1541.</author>
                  <author>Hermanni, Philippus.</author>
                  <author>Hester, John, d. 1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Iohn Charlwood],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno, Dominj. 1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by John Hester, of the German by Paracelsus.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Syphilis --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9025:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9025:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An excellent Treatiſe teaching howe to cure the French-Pockes: with all other diſeaſes ariſing and growing thereof, and in a manner all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſickneſſes.</p>
            <p>Dravvne out of the Bookes of that learned <hi>Doctor and Prince of Phiſitians, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtus Paracelſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Compiled by the learned Phillippus Herma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Phiſition and Chirurgion. And now put into Engliſh by Iohn Heſter in the Spagiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Arte, practitioner.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed. Anno, Dominj. 1590.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9025:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9025:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the worſhipfull the Maiſter VVardens, and generall Aſsiſtants of the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie of Chirurgions in London: <hi>Iohn Heſter</hi> wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth them all the true direction to the perfect way of knowledge in their Science, according to their profeſſion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had tranſlated out of the Germaine tongue into Engliſh, this little treatiſe of the French Pockes (a worke of more worth then the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Bulcke peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may ſeeme to import) I aduiſed with my ſelf a while to whom I might beſt aſsigne the patronage thereof, and meeting with no one degree, from the Prince to the Peſant, that woulde not highly ſcorne and diſdaine a matter of ſo baſe and vile a reckoning, as harſhe to the hearing of many, as it is in the feeling of others odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, I found none likelier to giue countenaunce there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, then you my Maiſters of chirurgerie, who by the profeſsion therof, maintain no ſmal part of your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinaunce, <hi>Leuis eſt labor cum lucro.</hi> And though there be among you at this day ſome, which to the profit of the reſt, by theyr writings haue trauailed therein wyth commendations, others, that by their painefull and dilligent cares, haue endeuoured many harde and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous cures of this filthy diſeaſe: yet beare with me I pray you, if after ſo many learned and wel experienced men, I alſo (the meaneſt of many) bring foorth with the poore widdow my little poore myte: and yet ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:9025:3"/>ſo little nor ſo poore, but that the intelligent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhall find as well in the diſcourſe, matter worth the diſcouerie, as in practiſe, Medicines worthy the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>In the preparing of which Medicines, if leaning to myne Author, I ſeeme to leaue others of more auten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique credit, neyther blame mee, nor condemne him, but waying the caſe in ballance of indifferencie, alowe vs ſo farre forth to follow the authoritie of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, as they haue or doe follow the trueth it ſelfe; a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie which hetherto the beſt men haue euer challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: and ſure in my opinion, theſe fellowes that to fill large volumes, rather ſet downe what other men haue ſaid, then what they ſhould haue ſaid, as many of our VVriters now adaies doe, thinking him the beſt Clark that voucheth moſt Authors, neyther waying theyr reaſons, nor pondering their proofes, but hudling run on with <hi>ipſe dixit,</hi> I ſay theſe fellowes, by blotting a great deale of good paper with much ſuperfluous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, lead a great many good wits a woolgathering, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing them to ſeeke for that they neuer finde, or els to find ſomewhat not woorth the ſeeking. For who I pray you of any iudgment, woulde ſeeke in <hi>Gallen</hi> or <hi>Hipocrates,</hi> men in cuery wiſe mans cenſure, without doubt, well woorthy the credit they are in, who I ſay would ſeeke in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or their Appothecaries, Medicines for diſeaſes whereof they neuer tooke notice. I denye not but theyr method may well be followed, euen ſo farre as generall rules may preſcribe in particular acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but to be tyed to a Medicine neither applyed nor approoued by them, is more then they allowed in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb facs="tcp:9025:3"/>or (for ought that I ſee) more then others ſhold allowe to them. Now that the diſeaſes of the French Pocks was neyther knowne to them, nor to theyr ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors for many yeeres, (although I know ſome auer it to be <hi>Lepram Arabum</hi>) is a matter ſo farre out of que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, that it refuſeth all ſhew of diſputation, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as this latter age of ours ſuſtaineth the ſcourge thereof, a iuſt whyp of our lycentiouſnes, ſo let it, (if there be any to be had) carry the credite of the cure, as ſome rewarde to ſome mens induſtries: neyther let vs peeuiſhly diſtruſt our owne wittes, furniſhed with ſo many helpers, and apiſhly admire other mens, onelie for theyr antiquitie: this were to tie God to times and ſeaſons, &amp; to play bopeepe in a ſecure ſhroude of idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vtterly diſ-franchizing our ſelues of the free le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacie, <hi>Dij laboribus dona dant ſua.</hi> Great curteſie is made who ſhall carrie the name, the Frenchman po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting it ouer to the Spaniard, the Spaniarde to the Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan, and either of theſe returning it back to other, but I would we in England were not as deeply intereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the thing, as either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are in the name, which becauſe I feare we are, as knowing more herein then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie man knowes, I thought good for the benefite of ſuch as are diſtreſſed, to deliuer to the Chirurgion, that which many (I am ſure) haue not yet ſeene: offering therewithall my paines, labour, and induſtry, as well in the preparation of Medicines heere ſet downe, as in any other, by any of my freendes otherwiſe prooued by experience, all yours, and freende to euery one of you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Hester.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:9025:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>IN this Booke I haue taken vpon me (gentle Reader) to deſcribe the ground and the original of the diſeaſe called the Pockes, and therewithall to correct the abuſes which haue hetherto been vſed in the curing thereof, as namelie in fumigation, washing, annointing, opening of tumours and ſuch like, and (the abuſes beeing corrected) I meane to shew (God willing) how they may be vſed without anie perrill to the Patient, and further to teach you a rare waie (with Lignum Guaiacum, commonly called Pockwood) how to care your Patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts going about their buſines, after a more better and perfect manner then heeretofore hath beene taught, wherby you may miniſter helpe and comfort to the forſaken and comfortles Patient, and may be able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that which both you promiſe to him, and he expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at your hand, that is to ſay the recouery of his former health, for which he ſo greatly longeth. But there are many now adaies, which take cures in hand, which neither know the diſeaſe, nor the manner of curing of it, &amp; yet they dare promiſe health to the Patient: theſe men goe to work with their Patients as the blind man doth with the Crow, at all aduentures, for they minister that to the diſeaſe, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth nothing at all to it, and ſo in ſteed of health, they giue the Patient his bane. For redreſſe whereof, and that you may the better take heed of ſuch, I haue therfore writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten this little Booke, which dooth teach you perfectly to cure the aforeſaid diſeaſe without any danger, ſo that the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent after that he is cured, shall be more healthfull in all his body the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was before ſuch time as he firſt got this diſeaſe, but for your better vnderstanding of that which is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, I wish you with dilligence to read that which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. And ſo fare yee well.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:9025:4"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Table contayning the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall matters in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <head>The firſt part.</head>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F the Pockes, howe to know them, &amp; the cauſe whereof they ſpring. Folio. 1.</item>
               <item>Of the abuſe vſed in curing of the Pockes, by annointing or ſaluing. fol. 5.</item>
               <item>Of fumigation or ſmoaking, with correction of the abuſe vſed therein. fol. 9.</item>
               <item>Of waſhing with Water. fol. 14.</item>
               <item>The correction of this waſhing with Mercurie. fol. 16</item>
               <item>Of launcing or opening of Tumors. fol. 17.</item>
               <item>An attractiue Playſter. fol. 18.</item>
               <item>Of curing the Pockes by ſweating. fol. 19</item>
               <item>The Drinkes which are vſually giuen for the Plague. fol. 20.</item>
               <item>The correction of ſweating, whereby the Pockes may bee cured. fol. 21.</item>
               <item>The preparing of Mercurie to prouoke ſweat. fol. eodem.</item>
               <item>Of curing the Pockes by Seege, with laxatiue Medicines. fol. 24</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The ſecond part.</head>
               <item>Of the nature or vertue of the Woode called Lignum vitae, or Guaiacum. folio. 29.</item>
               <item>Howe to chooſe this Wood, and which is the beſt. fol. 32.</item>
               <item>Howe to prepare the Drinke. fol. 34.</item>
               <item>What regiment the Patient is to obſerue. fol. 37</item>
               <item>Of the great paine in the head, which taketh away the ſleepe. fol. 40.</item>
               <item>The curing of the paines in the head of thoſe that are Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick, and Mellancholick. fol. 42</item>
               <item>Of madnes or idlenes of the head called Inſania. fol. 43</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9025:5"/>
How to cure the Phlegmaticke &amp; the Mellancholicke of this diſeaſe. fol. 44.</item>
               <item>Of the Falling-ſickneſſe, called in Latine Epileptia. fol. 45.</item>
               <item>The curing of the falling ſickneſſe in Phlegmatick and Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholick perſons. fol. 47.</item>
               <item>Of Polipus an ill diſeaſe in the noſe, whereof commeth the Cancer. fol. 48.</item>
               <item>Howe to cure the Phlegmatick and Mellancholicke of this diſeaſe. fol. 49.</item>
               <item>Of ſhortneſſe of winde, coughes, and ſtuffings in the breaſt. fol. codem</item>
               <item>The drinke for the Phlegmaticke and the Mellancholicke. fol. 50.</item>
               <item>Of the diſeaſes in the ſtomacke, as paines, queſineſſe, vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, &amp;c. fol. eodem</item>
               <item>For the Phlegmatick and the Mellancholicke, howe hee is to be cured. fol. 51.</item>
               <item>Of diſeaſes of the Liuer, as obſtruction, Apoſteme and the Dropſie. fol. 52.</item>
               <item>To cure the diſeaſes of the Liuer in Phlegmaticke and Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholick Patients. fol. 53.</item>
               <item>Of the diſeaſes of the Mother, as the ſuperfluous iſſue of menſtrues, and to ſtay them, and of barrennes. fo. 55</item>
               <item>To cure the diſeſes of the Mother in the Phlegmaticke and Mellancholicke Women. fol. eodem</item>
               <item>To cure the Cancer in any place of the body, whereſouer. fol. 56</item>
               <item>To cure the Cancer in cold complexions. fol. 57</item>
               <item>Of all other Vlcerations, whether they come of the Pockes or otherwiſe. fol. eodem</item>
               <item>For the Phlegmatick and the Mellancholick. fol. 59.</item>
               <item>Howe to cure the Rupture. fol. eodem</item>
               <item>To cure the ſame in Phlegmaticke and Mellancholicke per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. fol. 60</item>
               <item>Of Podagra or the Goute. fol. 61.</item>
               <item>To cure the Phlegmaticke and Mellancholick therof. fol. 62</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:9025:5"/>
               <head>Capit. 1. Of the Pockes, hovv to knovv them, and the cauſe whereof they ſpring.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O knowe the originall of this filthie ſickneſſe, there is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther regard to be had, then to the onely act of intemperancie, for the chéefe cauſe thereof, was the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the heauens, which in the very inſtant when this diſeaſe firſt ſhewed it ſelfe, did ſo ſtrongly infect the ſecret parts both of man and woman, that thereby the ſaid diſeaſe (firſt in the Parents, and after in the children) hath with a certaine ſecret poiſon, infected and ſpoiled the whole bodie, ſhewing it ſelfe commonly (though not alwaies) in the ſecret parts. For thoſe parts by the influence of the ſtars are firſt of all infected, and then the perſon ſo infected, giuing him ſelfe to incontinence, dooth cauſe the ſaide diſeaſe to ſhewe it ſelfe, firſt in the ſecret parts, and afterwards throughout the whole bodie, and béeing infected themſelues, doo alſo ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der infected children, as they alſo doo that are infected with the Leproſie. For the Leproſie and this diſeaſe are ſo neere of kinne, that they are Cozen-germanes to each other, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch infected perſons, muſt of neceſſitie begette corrupt children, becauſe that their ſéede is alſo infected, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſuch children are yet more corrupt, by reaſon of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt milke that they ſucke from their Mothers: ſo that it is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:9025:6"/>almoſt impoſſible to cure the ſaide children the diſeaſe béeing ſo rooted in them. Firſt through the infection of the ſeede, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and next of the milke: but ſuch children ſo borne and nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, are ſometimes not ſo greatly troubled with open ſores and botches as their Parents haue béen, but they haue many greefes and paines in their hodies, ſo that it ſhold ſéeme that they are not troubled with this diſeaſe, but with the Gout or ſome ſuch like, notwithſtanding it is nothing els but the Pockes, but that it chaungeth by meanes of generation, and the complexion of the child which differeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Parents. Theſe two, to witte, the influence or impreſſion of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and the generation, are the firſt and principall cauſes of this diſeaſe, and for that the influence is partly paſt and gone, we may alſo perceiue the furie of this diſeaſe to be part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie aſſwaged, and therefore not ſo terrible as it hath beene, and the older it is, the feebler it becommeth, but though the Pockes doo vaniſh away, yet there ſpring other diſeaſes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowe, different from thoſe that heeretofore haue raigned, ſo that we are enforced to ſéeke for newe remedies to heale the ſaid new diſeaſes. For euery diſeaſe hath his proper remedy wherewith to be cured, and vntill the ſame remedie be vſed, the Patient cannot be holpen, but is the longer the more ſpoiled, vntill in the ende there commeth one, who by chance vſeth the right remedie, and ſo ignorantly by good fortune healeth the Patient. Whatſoeuer ſhall be needfull to the curing of the Pocks or any other diſeaſe ſpringing thereof, ſhal by Gods helpe be perfectlie taught in this Booke, ſo that nothing ſhall be wanting therein.</p>
               <p>To proceede now with other cauſes of diſeaſes, you ſhall vnderſtand that there are many other cauſes beſides thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mencioned: for though thoſe are the principall, yet it chaunceth notwithſtanding, that ſome doo fall into thys foule diſeaſe, which through the impreſſion or influence were not ſo much inclined thereto, and that chaunceth through compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying with women, where through the ſecret parts are firſt infected, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood throughout the whole body, &amp; laſtlie the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:9025:6"/>newes, the fleſh and the bone. It happeneth alſo a man to be infected by ſweat, and that commeth by lying with another, for when one man lieth with another that is infected, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me doo ſweat ſore, hee muſt needes be infected with the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome of his ſweate. But this infection dooth not alwaies chaunce, for if the perſon infected haue had it a long time, and that it doth not appeare outwardly, but lyeth hidden inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, he dooth not infect ſo ſore, nor ſo ſoone as thoſe that are but newlie infected with it. Therefore let euery man take heede, that he doo not lye with them whom he knoweth not, for that it is very dangerous, therfore I counſaile euery man to haue great regard heereof, to eſchew ſuch a danger.</p>
               <p>Now we will ſhewe the ſignes whereby one may knowe when any man is infected with this diſeaſe, for a thouſand are taken in hande to be cured with the receipts for the Pockes, which are not infected therwith, but with ſome other diſeaſe, as the Goute, the Dropſie, and ſuch like, theſe and other moe as are all old Ulcers, and other infections of the ſkinne, are altogether, or for the moſt part, taken in hande to be cured with ſuch remedies, as pertaine properly to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pocks, which happeneth oftentimes, to the great hurt of the Patient, yea to his vtter ruine. Therefore you ought to take great héede that you vſe not the remedies pertaining to the Pockes, till ſuch time as you knowe perfectly, that the diſeaſe ſpringeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no other cauſe but the Pockes. Therefore you ſhal learn to know it thus.</p>
               <p>When this diſeaſe doth firſt attach any man, hee doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies feele great pricking and ſhooting betwéene the ſkinne and the fleſh, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he beginneth to were warme, it trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth him ſo that he cannot abide it, and whoſoeuer hath not (for a certaine ſpace) felt or béene greatly troubled with ſuch pricking or ſhooting, although their diſeaſe ſeeme ouglie or lothſome, yet it is not ſo ill as they ſuppoſe, but is ſprung of ſome other cauſe. And if a man chaunce to get any infirmitie in his ſecret part, as botches, running, or ſuch like, and haue not felt the ſaid ſigne of pricking or ſhooting, you ſhall then
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9025:7"/>know, that as yet no certaine iudgment can be giuen, for ſuch infirmities come ſometime before the ſigne can ſhew it ſelfe, but when the wound is healed vp, and that nature is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently purged, then commeth the aforeſaid ſigne, and the other euill diſeaſes ſometimes many yeeres after. But to inſtruct you perfectly in all thinges, you ſhal vnderſtand, that this diſeaſe taketh place firſt of all in the ſinewes, vppon the bones, and in all the ioynts of the bodie, ſo that it is verie hard to be knowne from the Goute, becauſe it alſo doth ſhew it ſelfe alwaies in thoſe places: but the paine of the Pockes is alwaies greater in the eueninges then in the morninges, and dooth encline to an Ague. And alwaies (this excepted) thou ſhalt haue regard to the aforeſaide ſignes of pricking or ſhooting, for if thoſe ſignes want, it is not the Pocks, but the Goute or ſome other colde diſeaſe. And if the Patient haue many open holes very redde and inwardly white, which doo not greatlie ſpread abroade, but continue at one ſtay without much matter, and will by no meanes heale outwardlie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand alſo the ſame to be a great ſigne, yet not ſo great as the firſt: for if the firſt ſigne of pricking haue not appeared, it is no ſufficient token of the Pockes, but ſome other diſeaſe proceeding of Melancholie.</p>
               <p>There are yet many other ſignes of the Pockes, as great Biles, with great paine in the head, and many redde puſhes on the fore-head, vnder the hayre, and in the necke, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though theſe doo reſemble the Pockes, and that very néerely, yet you may not iudge them to be the Pockes, vnleſſe the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid ſigne haue gone before, becauſe that is the moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine token of all other, and if ſo be that that haue ſhewed it ſelfe, then doubt not, for it is without all doubt that they are the Pockes, and ſo much the ſtronger as there hath beene greater Biles, or holes as aforeſaid where Biles haue béen, and alſo if there be great paine in the members, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more in the euening then at other times of the day, and that the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid ſigne haue appeared, then you neede not doubt it to be the Pockes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:9025:7"/>
Thus much of the Pockes, with the ſignes thereof, nowe ſhall be ſhewed the meanes to cure them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. 2. Of the abuſe vſed in the curing of the Pocks, by annointing or ſaluing.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt abuſe of thoſe that with annointing or ſaluing thinke to cure this foule diſeaſe, ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth of this, that they doo not knowe the dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and therefore they can giue no good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell thereto. For howe is it poſſible to heale a diſeaſe which a man neither knoweth, nor the nature of it? For a man ſhall as ſoone ſpoile it as heale it, with that which blindly and without vnderſtanding he doth miniſter vnto it. The ſeconde error is, in the compoſition of their receipts, which they doo ſo wonderfullie ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble together through their blind ignorance in the diſeaſe, that it is a great wonder that they bring not moe men to the graue then they doe, although they kill enowe, and too many toe. Therefore to ſhunne theſe inconueniences, we will teach thee to cure thy Patients by a better manner of annointing, whereof ſhall not onely enſue no perrill, but alſo the health of the Patient, according to thy will &amp; his owne deſire. But firſt, to make their error more manifeſt, I will ſette before thine eyes the ſimples whereof they compound their receipts, whereby thou maiſt perceiue what abuſe is in them: the ſimples are theſe. <hi>Euforbium, Staphiſagria, Scamonea, Sal gemmea, Lapis Calaminaris, Pepper, Ginger, Camphier, Vermelion, Axungia, Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Bolus armenus, Terra ſigillata, Common gumme, Ceruſe, Litargirium, Minium, Crued quickſiluer, Mercurius ſublimatus, Mercurius precipitatus.</hi> Theſe with other things moe, which they ought not to doo, they vſe in their annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which are hurtfull in diuers reſpects. And firſt becauſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9025:8"/>they doo vſe laxatiue Medicines which are very hurtfull to be vſed in ſuch manner without the bodie. For Mercurie béeing a thing that dooth pierce ſo ſore, doth alſo draw the other lax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atiues with him into the bodie, and they both béeing ſo veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and ſo extreame hote, doo infect the blood in the vaines, and inflame the whole bodie in ſuch ſorte, that nature (after ſhe is lightned of her burden, and diſcharged of that which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed her, muſt alone heale y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſeaſe) cannot by any meanes recouer herſelfe, but by reaſon that ſhe is ſo ſore pined, is not able to make any reſiſtance but remaineth vanquiſhed, ſo that the Patient is brought to a conſumption, or to the Dropſie, or els to death, therfore you ſhall in no wiſe vſe any laxatiues thereto, howe light ſo euer they be, becauſe they are alwaies hurtfull, and not profitable, ſor of all that is vſed in curing the Pockes, there is nothing that dooth anie way profit bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing outwardly miniſtred, but onely Quick ſiluer, therefore they are greatlie deceiued, which with ſtrong Purgations doo purge the Patient, thinking thereby to expell the matter of the Pockes by ſtooles, which is vnpoſſible, other wiſe then by purging with Mercurie, and béeing purged therewith, hée doth expel it by ſtooles, but there are not many that haue the knowledge to bring Mercurie to that ſtrength of purging, for it is a noble ſecret: and it is alſo neglected of the moſt parte, becauſe of the great labour and cunning that is to be vſed in preparing of it. But I will ſufficiently inſtruct them in the Chapter that followeth.</p>
               <p>Nowe for the correction of thoſe things that are needefull to be corrected in the annointing. Firſt and formoſt you ſhall eſchew all laxatiues, and all other thinges before mencioned, onely Mercurie excepted, for it is that which in the annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting performeth the action, and without Mercurie there is nothing profitable in this diſeaſe miniſtred outwardlie, but inwardlie there are manie noble remedies beſide Quickſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, which both in this, and alſo in all other diſeaſes, are of great force, ſo that the like hath not oft times been ſeene. But becauſe in this Booke we haue taken in hand to write onelie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9025:8"/>of the Pockes, wee will therefore meddle with nothing but Mercurie. In theſe two we will vſe ſuch dilligence, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall be vnpoſſible for you to helpe in this diſeaſe, if ſo be that you follow our counſaile.</p>
               <p>Nowe to prepare your Mercurie that it may outwardlie be miniſtred without perrill to the Patient: you ſhall take in Gods name of the earth wherin Mercurie groweth, which is found in Dutch-land in the gold &amp; ſiluer Mines, this earth is called in Dutch <hi>Berch ciuober,</hi> of this earth you ſhal take the ſofteſt which is not yet hardened, take twentie poundes thereof, this you ſhall beate and put it into a Kettle, &amp; poure fayre raine water thereto, and let it ſeeth an howre long, and the earth and the other filthineſſe will ſeperate it ſelfe, which you ſhall ſcumme off very cleane, then that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in the Kettle, you ſhall rub ſmall, and put it into a Cucurbit, and ſette it to diſtill vpon the fire with great heate, (according as I haue taught you in my Booke of Minerall diſtillations) and you ſhall ſee a white iuyce ariſe like Milk. And when you perceiue that it will drop no more, then take that white iuyce, and ſette it alone to diſtill in <hi>Balneo marie,</hi> and the moiſture that is thereby, will come alone, and in the bottome of the Cucurbit there will remaine an Oyle, as hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie in a manner as Quicke ſiluer, (the manner to diſtill by <hi>Balneo marie,</hi> I haue ſhewed you ſufficiently in my Booke of the diſtillation of Hearbes, to which Booke I referre you for breuities ſake.)</p>
               <p>The Oyle remaining in the bottome of the Cucurbit, as afore ſaid, you ſhall take and vſe to annoint withall as folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Take two ownces of the aforeſaid Oyle, and ſixe ounces of Spike Oyle, theſe you ſhall mingle together and warme them a little vpon the fire, and therewith annoint the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed parts of the Patient, but thoſe parts which are not diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you ſhal not annoint therewith, becauſe it would doo more hurt then good, for that there is no matter whereuppon they may worke, and not finding other matter to worke vpon, it would drie vppe the naturall moyſture from thoſe parts, but
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9025:9"/>the diſeaſed parts you ſhall annoint as aforeſaid in euery part or ioynt, and if there be any holes or blaines, you ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint thoſe alſo in the euening when he goeth to bed, and you ſhall couer him very warme that he may ſweat, and let him lye and ſweat two houres long, and he muſt not in any wiſe ſtirre himſelfe, becauſe he may ſweat the better, the ſayde time being expired, you ſhall abate the clothes from of him, and giue him warme cleane clothes, that he may drie vp the ſweate cleane in euery place, and beeing well dryed, take off his wette ſhirt, and put him on a cleane ſhyrt well warmed, then ſette him by a good fire of Oken wood, and dry his heade with warme clothes, in the meane while make his bedde, and lay on a payre of cleane ſheetes well warmed, then let him goe to bedde againe before it be colde, but couer him not too warme, but that he may ſleepe quietly. In the morning whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he awaketh, you ſhall vſe as you did in the euening, to witte, with fire and drying, and béeing well dryed of his ſweat, you ſhall apparrell him, and let him waſhe his hands and his face in warme water, and then let him eate his meat, which ſhall be ſuch as heere followeth.</p>
               <p>Firſt he ſhall eate no Swines fleſh, nor no ſalted fleſhe, no Hares, Conies, Harts, nor other veniſon, nor no Cowes fleſh, nor no pottage, but broth made of good Mutton, ſodden with Borage and a fewe Beetes and with a good deale of Bor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>age, other Pottage he ſhall eate none, he ſhal eate good Mutton, Hennes, Partriges, and all manner of wild foule, excepting all water foules, and all that ſeeke their liuing or ſwimme in the water, for that their fleſhe is ill to digeſt for a ſicke man, ingendering naughtie and mellancholie blood, hee may alſo eate good young Beefe, beeing newlie killed, and not long ſalted, but he muſt not eate much of it, becauſe it is hard of digeſtion for a weake ſtomack: but of all other there is nothing better for ſuch a Patient, then good young Kiddes fleſh that yet ſucketh his damme, with good Partriges and good young Hennes, he ſhall not refuſe to eate, for that of all other meates they are beſt: hee ſhall abſtaine from Pepper,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9025:9"/>and Ginger, but in his meate he may vſe Cinamon, Cloues, and ſuch like, alſo Nutmegges and Saffron: he ſhall alſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from Onions, Garlike, Skallions and ſuch like, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rawe or ſodden, becauſe they vexe the blood and inflame and dry vp the Liuer. His drinke ſhall be good Reniſh wine, tempered with water ſodden w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Annis ſeedes, Barlie, and Maſticke, of each as much as a Cheſtnut, of this water hée ſhall take one part, and of Wine two parts, and hée ſhall drinke thereof vntill he be cured: he ſhall keepe himſelfe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie warme, and out of the ayre within the houſe, he ſhal kéepe the windowes and the doores ſhut: this order he ſhall in all reſpects keepe with annointing, ſweating, and diet, vntil he be perfectly cured, for if he do as is aforeſaid, he ſhal vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly, by Gods helpe be cured, although hee had it twentie yéeres, if ſo be he haue not béen ſpoiled with other Medicines before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 3. Of fumegation or ſmoking, with correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the abuſe vſed therein.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is yet another way of curing the Pocks, found out by practitioners, for when they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that of force they muſt vſe Quicke ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, they tooke and killed it with Brimſtone, making Cinober thereof, becauſe it ſhould not be knowne to be Quicke ſiluer: for the common people, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing ſo manie to be ſpoiled and killed with Quicke ſiluer, woulde not willinglie be cured therewith: therefore becauſe they might the better vſe it without gaineſaying of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, therefore they brought it into another forme, vſing it alſo after another manner without any annointing, becauſe annointing was become odious to the Patient, therfore they found out a deuice to perfume or ſmoke the Patient, with the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9025:10"/>ſmoke of Cinober or Vermelion and ſo to cure him, for they knew Quick ſiluer to be ſo ſubtill or piercing, that they wold enforce it into the bodie at anie place, through the pores or ſweat holes. And therfore they ſet the Patient vnder a Tent or Canopie naked, with a Chafingdiſh of coales between his legges, wherin they ſtrowed the Cinober, ſtopping him cloſe round about, the Patient then beginning to ſweat, the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie with his whole ſubſtaunce creepeth into him in ſuch ſort, that it cauſeth all the ſlime in his bodie to aſcende into his mouth, infecting and corrupting all parts of the Patient in ſuch ſort, that it is pittifull to behold, ſo that the one after long Martirdome at length creepes into his graue, the other becommeth cripple and deformed, the thirde toothleſſe, and ſuch like miſerable accidents which are befallen them, that it would greeue a man to ſée, how they haue handled a number of their Patients.</p>
               <p>For Mercurie béeing vſed corporallie, hath this nature, that it dooth draw all the corrupt matter of the Pockes into the mouth, and becauſe they haue dealt ſo diſorderly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, taking more of it then they ought, they haue therwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all drawne the corruption into the mouth in ſuch abundance, that it could not haue ſufficient egreſſe, but for want thereof is returned, and hath ſought him a place in the entrailes, as in the Liuer, the Lunges, the Milte, and the ſtomacke, &amp;c. So that ſome are fallen into the diſeaſes of the Lunges, as Pluriſies, ſhortneſſe of breath, Coughes, conſumptions, and ſuch other, almoſt altogether incurable diſeaſes. Others are fallen into diſeaſes of the ſtomack, as vomitings, queſineſſe, great and intollerable paines, and Apoſtoms of the ſtomack, not beeing able to digeſt any good nouriſhment. Others are fallen into diſeaſes of the Liuer, as the yellow Iaundies, or Ictteritia, the Dropſie, the Bloodie flixe, hote firie Agues, and ſuch like. And ſome into the diſeaſes of the Milte, as the Feuer quartaine, the Cancker, the Woolfe, the Leproſie, to all which diſeaſes they were not any way ſubiect or inclined, vntill ſuch time, as they were brought thereto by the vnſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9025:10"/>of fooliſh Chirurgions, and all theſe aforeſaide diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, are altogether in manner vncurable, and in the end dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. Wherefore I would wiſh euery man to take heed, not to deale with Mercurie in any ſuch ſorte as is before expreſſed. But if thou wilt vſe it in any ſuch order as heereafter ſhalbe ſhewed thee, it ſhall not onely not be hurtfull, but thou ſhalt alſo therwith performe that which thou promiſeſt to thy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, that is to ſay the curing of his diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>Nowe we will ſhewe wherewith they are wont, and doe yet perfume or ſmoke their Patients: the ſimples are theſe that followe: <hi>Cinober naturall, Mercurie calcined, Artificiall Mercurie ſublimed, Alipta, Muſcata, Cloues, Cinamon, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reos, Muske, Franckincenſe, Maſtick, Mirha,</hi> with other ſuch ſweete thinges. Theſe ſweet things they haue therefore ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, becauſe the Patient ſhoulde not ſmell the ſtinke of the Brimſtone &amp; the Cinober: but though at the firſt they haue not knowne him by the ſmell, yet in the ende hee hath made himſelfe knowne vnto them by the feeling, for that hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth his worke with great force, as thoſe Patients know verie well which haue had experience of him, for as a ſharpe poyſon, ſo goeth he to worke in all his operation. Their firſt and greateſt error therefore is, that they doo fume the whole bodie of the Patient, where as they ſhold not fume any more then the place where they know that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place deſireth to haue iſſue. For in all diſeaſes, nature hath her certaine emuncto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries or purging places, where through ſhe coueteth to purge her ſelfe. As ſometimes by ſtooles, ſometimes by vemits, and ſometime ſweating: but in this diſeaſe, ſhee hath more places to purge by, as the groyne, the arme-holes, and ſuch like, and ſometimes other open holes in other places of the body, where a man muſt ſmoke, and not in any other place. But for your further knowledge you ſhall vnderſtand, that Mercurie may be prepared in diuers manners, as laxatiue, opilatiue, coroſiue, and attractiue, and alſo diaphoreticke, ſo that it may be prepared according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſire of him that wil vſe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:9025:11"/>
But in this fumigation or ſmoking, the intent is onelie to make him attractiue, that is, to draw out of the bodie, that which is hurtfull or hinderſome to nature, but heerein our cunning Chirurgions haue both been deceiued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and thereby haue alſo ſpoyled their Patients, firſt in that they perfumed or ſmoked the whole body of the Patient, for by that meanes the venimous matter, which before occupied but one or two places of the body, they haue now drawn through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the whole bodie, ſecondly in vſing the Mercurie ſo groſſelie with his whole ſubſtaunce, and that in ſuch great quantitie, they haue alſo by that meanes brought their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients to vtter ruine, and thirdly, in that they haue mingled other thinges with the Mercurie, where as it is the Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie alone that muſt performe the action without helpe of any other thing, béeing outwardly vſed by fumigation.</p>
               <p>Nowe we will ſhew thee the manner or order to prepare it to be attractiue, with the correction of the abuſe heeretofore vſed in the miniſtring thereof. Although it hath chaunced ſometimes, that there hath a Patient or two beene cured by meanes of this aforeſaid fumigation, and alſo by annointing, yet you ſhall vnderſtand, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> came to paſſe alone through the goodneſſe of nature, which is willing to helpe herſelfe, and ſtrong to reſiſt and ouercome the violence of the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, but yet for one ſo cured, there hath beene tenne thereby ſpoyled, beſides thoſe that haue béene ſent <hi>ad Patres,</hi> to robbe Moles, but to eſchew all theſe inconueniences, you ſhal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare your Mercurie in this order.</p>
               <p>Take Cinober made by arte (not naturall Cinober, and beate it as ſmall as is poſſible, whereof you ſhall take one pound, and one pound of Salt Peter, mingle them very wel together, and ſet them to ſublime (as ſhall be taught you in another Booke, which ſhall intreate of the preparing of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals) the Mercurie béeing ſublimed, you ſhall grind it ſmal vpon a ſtone, then you ſhall take an inſtrument or Earthen pot of two ſpannes in length, very well glazed within, it ſhal be one ſpanne wide in the bottome, and the mouth ſhal be as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9025:11"/>wide as a bigge Apple, in this inſtrument you ſhall put of the aforeſaid Mercurie, one dramme at a time, and you ſhall ſet the Patient and the ſaide inſtrument in ſuch ſorte, that the mouth of the inſtrument may be placed vpon the emunctorie or place, where the diſeaſe deſireth his iſſue, and the other ende vpon a Chafingdiſh with coales, making it hote in ſuch order, that it may warme the emunctorie, but heereof you muſt take great heede, that you make it not ſo hote, that you cauſe it bodilie to aſcende, for this is the thing that hath kyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſo many, that the Mercurie with his venimous hote bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, hath beene enforced into the bodie of the Patient.</p>
               <p>Therefore you muſt haue great regarde, that you make your fire in ſuch reaſonable manner, that you doo not cauſe him to aſcende, but that his ſpirit or dampe alone may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the action, then you ſhall ſee the matter iſſue foorth in ſuch abundaunce, that the Patient ſhal thereby be deliuered from his diſeaſe. You ſhall hold the ſaid inſtrument with the Mercurie ſo made, hote vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emunctorie, the ſpace of halfe an howre at a time, and you ſhall vſe this manner of fumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation euerie night when the Patient goeth to bedde, and let him ſweat euery time in ſuch order as is afore ſhewed in the Chapter of annointing, vſing him in al points as is there ſpecified, to wit, in ſweating, in drying, &amp;c. In this order you may fumigate or ſmoke without any danger, if you take héed that the Mercurie doe not aſcend, ſo that you ſhall not onelie auoide all perrill in your curing, but ſhall alſo purchaſe to your ſelues, praiſe and thankes whenſoeuer you ſhall vſe it. Thus much of fumigation, with the correction of the abuſes therein vſed, now concerning waſhing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:9025:12"/>
               <head>Capit. 4. Of vvashing vvith water.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is yet another peece of cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning deuiſed by the ſubtill Pock-maiſters, which perceiued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they coulde not longer vſe their Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie without hurt or ſhame, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo without thanke of the Patient, for the Patients perceiuing the great perils that enſued by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing, &amp; how manie were ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſpoyled, woulde not anie longer truſt their annointing, and ſo fared it alſo with their fumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, for when they ſawe the numbers that thereby were killed, they feared, and woulde not anie longer be ſmoked: whereuppon the Pock-Maiſters, were enforced to prepare their Mercurie after another order, that hee might be more ſecret and vnknowne, that they might yet vſe him, for they wiſt wel, that without him there was no cure to be wrought, for as yet <hi>Guaicum</hi> was vnknowne, therefore they tooke ſublimated Mercurie, and ſodde it in <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> and wyth the ſaid <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> they waſhed the Patient: which is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſubtill and forcible manner of curing, and very perrilous, which manner of curing, I doo counſaile all men to leaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doone. But in this manner following, you ſhall not onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide all daunger, but ſhall alſo haue good ſucceſſe in your workes, which if (for the great labour and charge which is required in the preparing of your Mercurie) you will not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, I would wiſh you to leaue waſhing: for of all manners of curing, there is none the like for force and daunger, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you wil not otherwiſe correct your Mercurie, it is not lawfull for you to cure any man by waſhing, for that they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9025:12"/>which are this way cured, are in greater daunger then one man which dooth fight againſt two other for life and death. But if you will prepare your Mercurie as heereafter ſhal be ſhewed, you ſhall not onelie eſchew all daunger which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe may happen, but ſhall alſo performe as much as ſhal be requiſite to the curing of this diſeaſe, &amp; as much as hath béen hetherto performed by anie man, wherefore flie ſloth, and vſe diligence in preparing your Mercurie, whereby you ſhal not onely obtaine your deſire in curing the diſeaſe without feare and danger, but alſo with great credite to your ſelfe, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to the Patients.</p>
               <p>In this waſhing, beſides this afore written, there is yet another abuſe, that is, that they haue waſhed all the partes of the body, as well thoſe that were ſounde, as thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were diſeaſed, then the which they could not haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ouerſight, for by that means they haue brought the ſound parts into a worſe caſe then the diſeaſed, for Mercurie vſed in ſuch ſort, is in the operation as hote as fire, ſo that in thoſe partes wherein there is no corrupt matter to bee dryed out, there he goeth to worke, and drieth out all the good and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall moiſture, and thereby ſpoyleth the whole member.</p>
               <p>Therefore aboue all things you muſt take heede that you doe not waſh the whole parts, but onely thoſe that are diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for the diſeaſed parts haue matter, wherein the Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie may worke, and which is needfull to be dryed out. Nowe I will ſhewe you howe to prepare and to vſe your Mercurie, but firſt I will ſhewe you thoſe ſimples wherewith theſe Maſters vſe to waſhe, which are theſe. <hi>Mercurius ſublima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Auri pigmentum, Arſenicun, Ceruſa, Camphier, Aqua vitae.</hi> Theſe thinges if I ſhoulde miniſter in this ſorte crudlie without other correction, I thinke I ſhoulde kill all the Patients that I ſhoulde take in hande. For by reaſon of the ſtrength of the <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> the Mercurie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth ſo ſubtil and ſo fierie, that it is a great wonder that they die not all that are taken in hand to be cured in this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. For of all other, this manner of curing is moſt daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9025:13"/>for the Mercurie by his ſubtiltie, and by meanes of the heate of the <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> doth performe his operation in the inward parts of the Patient with ſuch force, as manie ſicke Patients haue better felt then I can deſcribe, and though this be moſt true, yet there are ſome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe it dailie, as though it were good, but I ſay that it is a ſecrete kinde of poyſon, which though it be but outwardlie applied, doth yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding (with great force) performe his worke inwardly in the bodie, for it inflameth and ſtirreth vppe the bloode in ſuch ſort, that the Patient oftentimes falleth a bleeding, bléeding themſelues to death, others are like to be choked, ſo forciblie draweth this venime to the hart, but peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ſome will defend his dooings herein, and ſay, I haue holpen many there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, but I would faine heare the Patient himſelfe report it, yet nouertheleſſe, I doe thinke well, that ſome one amongſt a hundred, may be cured by this meanes, but I conne them no thanke therefore, but rather nature, which herſelfe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the diſeaſe, and reſiſted the ſtorme, but howe manie haue they ſpoiled and holpen vnder the grounde before they haue cured one, verilie a great number I am certaine, but to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide ſuch a daunger, and to attaine credit in this arte, doo as is aforeſaid, leaue off your waſhing, or els prepare your Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie as followeth.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>The correction of this waſhing with Mercurie.</head>
                  <p>Take Mercurie which is ſublimed, by himſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any addition, as I will teache you in the fore alledged Booke, the ſame you ſhall ſublime yet foure times with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prepared Salt, then you ſhall poure vpon the ſaid Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie, good rectified <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> as I haue taught you to recte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it in my booke of Diſtillations. This <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> you ſhall ſet on fire with a little Paper, and let it burne till it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, then pouré on more, and doo likewiſe, dooing it ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vntill the Mercurie doo ceaſe to bite or eate vppon the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9025:13"/>tongue, then ſeeth the Mercurie in Perſic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ie water, or in Celendine water, halfe an houre long, then let it be colde, and poure of the water, that the Mercurie be not vſed with his bodie, but that his ſpirit &amp; his ſtrength may come foorth, and be coupled to the diſeaſe, for in the ſpirit of the Mercurie is the vertue to cure the diſeaſe, and in the bodie of it, is the force to kill and ſpoile the Patient. Therefore it is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ouerſight that may be, to take Mercurie and to ſeeth it in <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> and therewith to waſhe the Patient, for by that meanes, it entereth corporallie into the bodie of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and ſpoyleth and killeth him, as all other poiſons natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie doe, therefore take heed that in no wiſe you vſe it cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porallie, but onelie the ſpirit as is aforeſaid, and ſo nothing can enſue to the Patient, but good.</p>
                  <p>With the aforeſaid water ye ſhall waſhe or make wet, the diſeaſed parts of the Patient, euery night when he goeth to bedde, then you ſhall lay him to ſweate, vſing him in all points as is ſhewed in the other Chapter, and you ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue this manner of waſhing, euery day once, vntill ſuch time as he be perfectly cured, and that he feele no more pain. You need not feare to vſe this manner of curing in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, for if you do as I haue here taught you in this Chapter, there can happen nothing but good to the Patient, and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite to your ſelfe, ſo that you ſhall wonder to ſee what ſhall come to paſſe in this order of curing, ſo that you may wyth credite and a good conſcience, aſke your reward. Thus much concerning waſhing.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. 5. Of launcing or opening of Tumors.</head>
               <p>THere haue béene ſome that haue held opinion, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the great paines that men haue had on theyr ſhinnes, and the pypes of their armes, that therefore
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9025:14"/>the roote of the diſeaſe muſt needes lye there, (but they are deceiued, for the roote lyeth in the bloode) theſe going for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in their opinions, haue made holes vpon the ſhinnes, and diuers other places of the bodie, thinking that the dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe would haue runne out at thoſe holes, and ſo haue beene gone, but their expectation was deceiued, for although they had made the ſkinne full of holes, yet the matter they looked for, ranne not out at them, but there iſſued a certaine yellow water, which procéeded of the paine which the Coroſiue had made, and not any matter of the diſeaſe, neither did it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the Pocks any thing at all. But I find no great fault in this, for as it holpe not, ſo it hindered not, yet it was a great fooliſhneſſe of them to thinke the diſeaſe to be ſo cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardlie to giue ouer his hold before any aſſault were laid to it. But becauſe there may chaunce ſometimes, much matter to lie about the ſhins, or ſuch like places, which cauſeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable paines, to remedy the ſame you may vſe the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid meanes, to drawe away the ſaid matter, yet not as they did, for they did nothing but ſette open the doore, forgetting that which was moſt needfull, that is, when they had ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the place, they ſhould haue applied a Plaiſter, to haue drawne out the matter, which otherwiſe of it ſelfe woulde neuer haue come forth.</p>
               <p>But for your further helpe when any ſuch maines do hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen. I will ſette downe certaine thinges whereof you may make Plaiſters, and applie to ſuch open places, whereby the matter may be drawne forth, and the paine diminiſhed.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>An attractiue Plaiſter.</head>
                  <p>Take <hi>Serapini, Galbani, Amoniaci,</hi> of each two drams, <hi>Oppoponacis,</hi> foure drammes, <hi>Bdellij,</hi> ſixe drammes, diſſolue it in Vineger, then ſtraine it through a cloth, then ſéeth it ſo long till it beginne to waxe thicke, then put thereto of <hi>Rha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barbe</hi> two drammes, <hi>Radicis affodeli</hi> halfe a dramme, Yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Amber, two drammes, this you ſhall beate verie ſmall,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9025:14"/>and then vſe it. This draweth ſo forciblie, that it leaueth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vntouched. But becauſe this is no certaine rule for the curing of the Pockes, but onelie to diminiſh part of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, we will not ſtay anie longer about it, but proceed to the perfit curing of the ſame, and firſt of another manner of cure vſed by ſweating.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. vj. Of curing the Pockes by ſweating.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is yet another opinion ſprung vppe, and that is this, to cure the Pockes by ſweating. This came firſt out of Italie into Dutchlande or Germanie, and at length it became co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon heere in this Countrie: and indeede for ſome it was good, but for others hurtfull, for flegmaticke &amp; moiſt bodies, are thereby dryed and made curable, but the Cholle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke and Melancholick bodies, are thereby ſpoiled, not with the ſweating, but with the hote Medicines that they vſed to prouoke ſweate, which Medicines ſo enflamed and dryed vp the blood in the vaines, the Liuer, the Lungs, the Milte, and the Kidnies, that thereby manie Patients fell firſt into the Feuer quartaine, ſecondlie into the Dropſie, and laſtlie into the graue. Well the Pocks are not to be cured in this ſorte. For though it be good for one, yet is it hurtfull for annother, but if yee will cure, you muſt prouide ſuch remedies as may be good for all complexions, and hurtfull to none, eſpeciallie héere in ſweating.</p>
               <p>But for your better inſtruction, it ſhall be neceſſarie firſt to ſhewe you wherewith they vſe to prouoke ſweate. They haue taken good ſtrong Wine, and mingled the ſame with Treakle, and with other things which you ſhal heare anone, and giuen the ſame to the Patient to drinke, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> couered
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9025:15"/>him to make him ſweat, and this they haue ſo long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, vntill either the Patient was cured, or that they were hindered by hote Agues which they brought vpon the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, for by this meanes they had ſo ſpoiled the Liuer and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts with heate, that they coulde not any longer vſe their naturall ſtrength, but went backward, ingendering e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill black enflamed blood, which muſt needes bring forth A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues and the Feuer quartaine, therfore now I wil ſhew you the ſimples whereof they make their Medicine to prouoke ſweat, that you may the better eſchewe them, and theſe they are.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>The Drinkes which are vſuall giuen for the Plague.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> mingled with <hi>Treakle, Aqua vitae</hi> mingled with <hi>Camphier cardamomum, Grana paradiſi, Pepper, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forbium, Radix vngulae caballine, Radix flammule.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide theſe aforenamed, they haue yet vſed many other things, and moreouer deuiſed a meane to cauſe the Patient to ſweat of himſelfe, without helpe of any Medicine, and to performe the ſame, they vſed Crocks or great Earthen pottes, filling them with hote water, and ſtopping them ſo cloſe, that no moyſture could iſſue foorth, theſe they laid in bed by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and couered him with clothes in ſuch ſort, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> by meanes thereof, and the warmth of the Pottes together, they cauſed him to ſweat. This waie, though it be verie good to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke ſweat, yet in this diſeaſe it is not good, becauſe this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe dooth not ſuffer it ſelfe to be expelled ſo eaſilie, without other greater helpes, but in the Plague. This is a verie good waie and profitable, yet in this diſeaſe, ſweating is alſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie needfull. Nowe followeth the correction of this manner of ſweating.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="treatment">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:9025:15"/>
                  <head>The correction of ſweating, vvhereby the Pocks may be cured.</head>
                  <p>The pores or ſweat holes in the ſkinne, are alſo <hi>emunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torium,</hi> (that is to ſay a place wherethrough nature dooth purge herſelfe) yea one of the moſt principall emunctories, therefore through the ſaid pores or ſweat holes, a man may very well purge nature, and alſo expell the matter of the Pockes, but not through the heate of clothes, neither of the aforeſaid ſimples, as <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> and ſuch like, for the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid remedies they are not good for this purpoſe: but the ſtrength is in the Mercurie alone, and it is hee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> muſt worke the feate, that is, he can through ſweating, expell the matter of the Pocks, and knoweth alſo where to find it, for which cauſe he muſt be made to be diaphoreticke, that is, to expell ſweat by the pores, for beeing brought thereto, hee is ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till in his operation againſt the Pocks, that it is almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible, for he leaueth no corner in the whole body vnſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, expelling all the corrupt matter that he findeth. But the preparing of him (I feare me) wil be too troubleſome for lazie Practiſioners, and therefore I thinke I may ſpare my labour, yet notwithſtanding, I will reueale it for their ſakes that are dilligent, knowing that he that deſireth the health of his Patient, will ſpare no labour, nor refuſe any trauaile to obtaine the ſame, and therefore I will nowe ſhewe you the preparing of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>The preparing of Mercurie to prouoke ſweat.</head>
                  <p>Take of <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> a fourth parte, Tinne, and Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiluer, of each halfe an ounce, put this together in a Glaſſe, and ſette it in a Chafingdiſh with warme aſhes, (you muſt remember to put it into a Glaſſe, becauſe the <hi>Aqua fortis</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:9025:16"/>doth pierce through all thinges but onelie glaſſe, you muſt therefore take a Glaſſe with a flatte or round bottome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a foote, and put it therein, ſetting it in the aſhes as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) in the ende, when you perceiue the Quicke ſiluer to be diſſolued, take it out of the aſhes, and let it ſtand till one may ſay the <hi>Pater noſter</hi> thrée or foure times, and there will be a little ſand in the bottome, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poure off the cleere, putting it into another cleane Glaſſe, and ſette it againe in the aſhes as aforeſaid, and make vnder the Chafingdiſh a ſmall fire, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till you ſee the water be all dried or ſodden out, then let it bee cold and breake the Glaſſe, for otherwiſe you cannot gette it out it will be ſo hard, when you haue taken it out, you muſt grinde it ſmall vppon a ſtone, and put it in a ſmall veſſell of Siluer and gylt, or of golde, for that is beſt for this purpoſe, the ſaid Veſſell muſt be about the bigneſſe of a Spoone, and ſo deepe, that it may containe the ſaid matter, and that you may couer the ſaide matter with <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> the bredth of a finger. This veſſell you ſhall ſet in geod ſtrong wine Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, a little déeper then the ſaid matter that is in the Veſſel, and then ſette the <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> on fire that it may burne (note this, that your <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> muſt be rectified, that it do not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine any fleame, according as I haue taught you to rectifie it in my Booke of Diſtillations.) The <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> béeing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, you ſhall immediatlie poure on more, and let if like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe burne away, dooing this ſo often, vntill the Mercurie, with the tinne, doo conuert to a certaine kind of Oyle that is thicke and fat. Of this Oyle you ſhall take one graine &amp; min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle it with good Wine, and giue it to the Patient to drink in the morning faſting, and then couer him reaſonablie (not too warme) and you ſhall ſée that which will make you to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that is, you ſhall ſee ſuch aboundaunce of ſweat iſſue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Patient (though he be not verie warme couered) that wil cauſe you greatlie to maruell: and of this you may be bolde, that he ſhall ſweat ſo much as may be good and profitable for his nature and no more. This you ſhall giue him euery daie once, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſweateth, let him be wel dried with warme
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9025:16"/>and cleane clothes, and he muſt take dilligent heede to keepe himſelfe from cold, and out of the ayre, and that principallie when he ſweateth, his diet and his drinke ſhall be in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects as is afore ſpecified in the Chapter of ſweating, and you ſhall not regard what hath béene written heeretofore by diuers, concerning the not eating of ſalte, for that they haue therein greatlie erred, therefore you ſhall vſe ſo much ſalt as ſhalbe needfull for the ſeaſoning of your meat to giue it a good taſte.</p>
                  <p>But alwaies prouided you muſt vſe meaſure in all things, and that principallie in ſalt and ſowre thinges, becauſe that they two béeing two much vſed, are verie hurtfull to the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, and for that cauſe you muſt take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meſurablie, but in any wiſe not to vſe your meate without ſalte, for that ſalt is the onelie thing requiſite in the bodie, to preſerue the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours from corrupting, for in what part of the bodie ſoeuer the ſalte beginneth to loſe his vertue, in the ſame part imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatlie beginneth a filthy rotting, not much vnlike to the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, wherefore in any wiſe you ſhall not forbid your Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent the eating of ſalt, for by that outwarde ſalt, the inwarde ſalt (which is in the bloode, and in all the other parts of man) muſt be nouriſhed and maintained.</p>
                  <p>But that you may the better beleeue, that there is ſalte in all the parts of mans bodie, you ſhall vnderſtand, that the bodie of man (by all Philoſophers, and by me alſo) is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a little worlde, which was called (by them) <hi>Microcoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> which little world doth containe in it, all ſuch things as the great worlde dooth naturallie containe in her. By which reaſon it muſt alſo containe ſalt, yet not bodilie but ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and that this is true, a man may perceiue by this, that all whatſoeuer iſſueth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man, is altogether ſalt, as the teares, the ſweat, the vrine and ſuch like, wherefore it is neceſſarie for the Patient to vſe ſalt to maintaine the ſame as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
                  <p>But concerning Vineger, you ſhall vſe as little as is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, becauſe it is not onelie vnprofitable, but alſo hurtfull to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9025:17"/>nature, for which cauſe you may not vſe it much: the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent muſt alſo refraine from drinking too much ſtrong Wine, and principallie from ſowre Wine, ſo that his drinke ſhal be of the beſt and ſweeteſt Reniſh wine that can be gotten, and he muſt alſo drinke it meaſurablie, thus much concerning dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et and drinke. And heere you ſhall vnderſtande, that by thys manner of ſweating, all kinds of the Pockes may be cured, although they were neuer ſo ill, yea though one had had it xxx. yeeres long, ſo that to him that foloweth this preſcribed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of curing, there ſhall be nothing impoſſible (pertaining to this diſeaſe) but onelie that which God will not ſuffer to be cured, wherefore I would wiſhe you to vſe it, aſſuring you that you ſhall not find anie other meanes that ſhall be much better then this is. Thus much concerning ſweating.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. 7. Of curing the Pockes by Seege, vvith laxatiue Medicines.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Doctors of Phiſicke haue alſo herein tried all their cunning, &amp; vſed diuers meanes with laxatiue Medicines, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (as though it were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie agreeable to nature) they might by Seege expell the matter of the Pockes, but becauſe that nature diuers times chooſeth other emunctories to purge herſelfe by, therefore their deuices haue had no good ſucceſſe, for though there be manie remedies whereby to purge the bodie from his vncleannes, yet not one of them is able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer the bodie from this diſeaſe, wherefore I would not wiſh anie man to purge with any ſuch laxatiues, becauſe it is not onelie in vain, but alſo verie hurtful, for they doo not ſo much as once meddle or touch the matter of this diſeaſe, as beeing altogether vnable to expell the ſame, &amp; yet becauſe they muſt worke beeing once receiued in, they goe to worke vpon that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9025:17"/>which they ought not to meddle withall, expelling that which is profitable to nature: yea and béeing too often vſed, or in too great a quantitie, they doo expell the blood, the fleſhe, and at laſt they doo melt the marrow in the verie bones, expelling it alſo, according as wee haue ſeene the experience thereof in thoſe which thus haue béene purged, for their fleſh falleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie, theyr cheekes waxe hollow, they become leane and pale of colour, which palenes of colour ſo long continueth, as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture continueth vnable to clenſe the bloode, and to ouercome the diſeaſe. What auaileth it then to purge with ſharpe lax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atiues, when it is the nature alone that muſt heale the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.</p>
               <p>But I knowe there be many that will ſay, and I graunt it to be true, that by purging they haue cured diuers Agues, and ſuch like diſeaſes, but though it be graunted that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe healeth after ſuch time as the Patient is purged, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it is nature herſelfe which healeth the diſeaſe, after that her enemies are put to flight: but as for thoſe lax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atiues, they doo not ſo forſake the bodie of the Patient, but that they leaue manie reliques behind them, which afterward are the cauſes of manie great euils, &amp; alſo the body is brought thereby to ſuch a cuſtome, that it doth looke dailie to be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and therefore will not performe the accuſtomed digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as it ought to doo, and notwithſtanding all the euils that doo enſure theſe purgations, there is no helpe nor comfort to be expected of them toward the curing of this diſeaſe, becauſe they doo not ſo much as once touch it.</p>
               <p>Nowe I will ſhewe you wherewith they haue vſed to purge, to the end you may take heede of it, becauſe it cannot any thing profit you. Firſt they haue giuen the Patient of theſe Iuleps or Sirops, and after haue purged them with the laxatiues following. Theſe are the Iuleps and Sirops, <hi>Siru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus de fumo terre, Sirupus acetoſus, Simplex et compoſitus, Sirupus de Pomis compoſitus, Sirupus de menta, Sirupus de biſantijs, de Abſinthis, et Epitimo, de Cicorea, et de Eupato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria. Iulep violatum, et Iulep roſatum.</hi> In verie hote diſeaſes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9025:18"/>theſe aforeſaid Sirops they mingled with theſe diſtilled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters folowing, becauſe they might the better be receiued. The waters are theſe, <hi>Aqua boraginis, Aqua bugloſſe, Fumus ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rę, Aqua cuſcutę, Aqua meliſſę, Aqua ſcholopendrię, Aqua maioranę, Aqua finiculi, Aqua cicoreę, Aqua endinię, Aqua lupuli, Aqua capillorum veneris, Aqua eupatorij, Aqua lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucę, Aqua ſcabioſę, Aqua cardo benedicti.</hi> Theſe aforeſaid waters with other moe, they vſed to mingle with theyr Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropes, and then gaue them to the Patient to drinke, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the matter, and afterward purged them with theſe lax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atiues following. <hi>Diaſene, Diacitoniton, Diacarthami, Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus, Coloquintida, Turbith, Elleborus, Confectio, Hamech, Electuarium, Iudum, Diagridiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Ezula, Hermodactilus.</hi> And alſo with theſe Pilles folowing. <hi>Pillule cochię, Pillule indę, Pillule lucis, Pillule artecite, Pillule feditę, Pillule areę, Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lule de hermodactilis, Pillule de lapide armeno.</hi> Vpon all theſe aforeſaid, I will God willing ſhewe you the correction, but principallie vppon the laxatiues, for that the other neede not greatlie to be corrected.</p>
               <p>Firſt you ſhall vnderſtande, that it is not euill or hurtfull that the matter in the Liuer and the ſtomacke, be firſt prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and then afterward purged with theſe Medicines folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which are very eaſie and not burtfull to be vſed. Theſe are they, <hi>Diacatholicon, Caſſia fiſtula, Manna rhabarbarum, Aloes, Polipodium, Sena, Epitimum, Mirobolanorum</hi> fyue ſorts or kinds. For theſe helpe to lighten nature, &amp; to clenſe the blood of all vncleanneſſe proceeding of meate and drinke, they deliuer alſo from Agues if they be often vſed, &amp; are hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full neither to olde nor young, euerie man may vſe them with out daunger. But as for the matter of the Pockes, they doe not ſo much as once meddle with it, but let it lie ſtill vntou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. For that requireth another manner of force wherwith to be rouſed and driuen forth, which pertaineth to the Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie alone, for being brought to be laxatiue, he can find out that which the other could not find, and dooth expell that which he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9025:18"/>knoweth to be offenſiue to nature, not onely in this matter of the Pockes, but alſo in all other diſeaſes, therefore I coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile all men to vſe diligence in learning to make the Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie laxatiue, as hereafter ſhall be taught.</p>
               <p>The correction of this that hath béene ſaide, is nothing but this, that you purge with no other laxatiue but onelie with Mercurie, and to make him laxatiue, you muſt prepare him thus.</p>
               <p>Firſt you muſt haue a kind of water, that with extreame heate of fire is diſtilled of Egge-ſhels, of this water you muſt take foure ounces, of Quick ſiluer one ounce, and put them together in a Glaſſe, which Glaſſe you muſt ſette in a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingdiſh or ſome other thing with ſand, and ſette the Chafing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh in or vpon the fire, &amp; the Mercurie ſhall diſſolue through the force of the water, and being diſſolued, you ſhall diſtill of the water, and poure other vppon it, this you muſt doo ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, vntill the Mercurie become as redde as blood, when the water is drawne from it: this Mercurie is the right Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to expell the matter of the Pockes by ſtooles. The Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie then being as redde as bloode, you ſhall grinde it to fine powder, and of the ſaid powder you ſhall giue the Patient to drinke (with good ſweete Wine, or other Wine that is not ſowre) euery morning faſting three graines: or you may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo mingle it with <hi>Theriacle</hi> or <hi>Metridatum,</hi> and giue it him to eate euerie morning faſting, and let him faſt after it at the leaſt foure howres, and then ſhall he purge that, that is néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be purged, and is the right matter of the Pockes, and it ſhall not any way be hurtfull vnto him, but ſhall clenſe him from all vnhealthfull thinges, reſtoring him to a healthfull ſtate, clenſing all ſuperfluitie, and leauing all the other hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of the bodie vntouched.</p>
               <p>This is that, that purgeth the matter of the Pockes by the ſtoole, and there is no other laxatiue that is anie thing auailable, but onelie Mercurie beeing thus prepared. The Patient muſt be kept with meate and drinke, according as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9025:19"/>is ſaide of the other in the Chapters going before, he muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be kept from colde, &amp; out of the ayre, but principally from the companie of Women, becauſe that is the roote of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, which beeing frequented by the Patient, it renueth the diſeaſe, making it worſe and more venimous then before, therefore aboue all things that muſt be eſchewed. And thus much concerning the curing of the Pockes by Mercurie.</p>
               <trailer>Heere endeth the firſt part.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:9025:19"/>
            <head>The ſecond part of this Booke, which treateth of curing the Pockes vvith drinkes made of <hi>Lignum guaiacum,</hi> after a good and perfit order.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. I. Of the nature and vertue of the vvood called Lignum vitae, or Guaiacum.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His wood is found in the Ilands of the Indian ſea, and is as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon there, as our Oke is heere with vs, the people of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie doo vſe nothing of it but onely the leaues &amp; the ſmalleſt twigs, which they ſtampe ſmall, &amp; wring out the iuyce of it, and ſo drink it. But becauſe this Countrey is ſo far from vs, we cannot haue it ſo freſh, as to take and vſe the leaues as they doe, but are faine in ſteed thereof to vſe the boughes or braunches, and thereby to ſeeke helpe for the Patient, and ſo it is come to this paſſe, that of the ſaid braunches we make a certain decocted drink, by which the ſaid diſeaſe is cured. But yet there hath beene a great abuſe committed by diuers, as well in the making or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:9025:20"/>ſeething of this drinke, as alſo in the diets, with other like things, all which heereafter God willing ſhall be corrected. But ere we proceede heerein any further, I will declare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the nature and propertie of this wood.</p>
               <p>The auncients in times paſt haue had knowledge of this wood, and haue giuen it his name, although ſome men be of the contrarie opinion, ſuppoſing that they knew it not, yet I ſay that they are deceiued: for though in all points it doe not agrée with that which they call <hi>Hebena,</hi> yet I ſaie that it can not be anie other, but a certain kind of the ſaid <hi>Hebena.</hi> The auncients deſcribing the ſaid <hi>Hebena</hi> or <hi>Hebenum,</hi> doe ſaie, that it dooth not ſwim, but goeth to the bottome like a ſtone, and that within it is as blacke as ynke, and therefore ſome doo ſaie that this is not that <hi>Hebena.</hi> To ſuch wiſe men I aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, ſending them to <hi>Dioſcorides,</hi> willing them to marke his diſcription of herbes and flowers, &amp;c. For there he deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth many herbes and flowers, which if a man ſhould ſeeke for in that order which they are there deſcribed, I know they will ſcarcely be founde, becauſe they doe not in all points a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the diſcription: and the reaſon thereof is, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Countrie where the ſaid Herbes doo growe, for in one Countrey they are of one faſhion, and in another ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what different from the ſame, and ſometimes alſo by remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing from place to place, Flowers doo alter their colours, and become more double of leaues then they were before, and yet they remaine the ſame Flowers ſtill, euen ſo is it with <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bena,</hi> for that which groweth in India, is of another colour then that which groweth in Grecia, and yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is a kind of <hi>Hebena,</hi> for it goeth to the bottome, as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benum</hi> doth, and is alſo of the ſame vertue, curing the ſame diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>Hauing prooued that this Woode with his name haue beene knowne in olde time, we will nowe ſhewe his vertue and operation, what he worketh in the bodie of man, beeing miniſtred as it ought to be. The vertue of this wood is dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more then any other Medicine, and to driue away the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9025:20"/>opilations or ſtoppings of the Liuer and the Milte, being mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred with opening Medicines, according as ſhal be taught héereafter. It may be vſed (almoſt) in all diſeaſes, beeing vſed with ſuch Medicines as are appertinent to the diſeaſe, and béeing ſo vſed, his vertue is increaſed, and hee becommeth of more force. Howe to applie him with other Medicines, ſhall be taught in other Chapters that follow.</p>
               <p>But peraduenture you will muſe why I doo now ſo much praiſe this wood, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering that I haue ſo much before prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Mercurie, I ſay therefore that amongſt all other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, there is none that can be vſed with leſſe danger then this of <hi>Hebenum.</hi> Conſidering the great danger conſiſting in the Mercurie, by reaſon that he is ſo venimous, &amp; that there are ſo fewe which either can or will prepare him in ſuch or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as he ought to be prepared, as well for the laboure there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in required, as alſo the coſt and cunning that neceſſarily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth thereto. Theſe with other moe are the cauſes why we haue written thus in commendation of this Wood, prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it to be the beſt and moſt ſureſt in the curing of this fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie diſeaſe, excepting onelie the well prepared Mercurie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as wee haue mencioned and taught in the Chapters before going: but as I ſay, Mercurie beeing excepted (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all other Medicines) there is none comperable to this <hi>Hebenum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For beeing vſed in ſuch order as it ought to be, it may be miniſtred without all daunger, as well in hote and drie, as alſo in cold and moiſt complexions: and dooth alſo work great wonders in many diſeaſes, ſuch as are almoſt incredible, but it muſt be vſed orderlie, as in the Chapters following ſhalbe taught at large, wherein the curing of eache diſeaſe ſhall be taught you in ſuch good order, that thereby you ſhall perceiue how greatlie they haue béen deceiued, which (after one man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with this aforeſaid drinke) haue taken vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to cure all manner of diſeaſes. Euen like a Shoomaker which would make euery mans ſhoes vpon one laſte, which is impoſſible. Now we will proceed to the chooſing of this wood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:9025:21"/>
               <head>Capit. 2. Hovve to chooſe this VVoode, and which is the beſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou ſhall take and vſe the young and ſmall braunches with the barke vpon them if they be freſh, and haue not béene long gathered, if you may ſo haue them, if not, then you ſhall take of the biggeſt hauing the barke vppon them, becauſe that as they are greater and thicker, ſo they are harder, and drie not ſo ſoone as the leſſer braunches doe, for if you take the ſmall ones, hauing beene long gathered, they will be too drie, therfore it is beſt to take the olde being gathered both at one time. For if a man might haue it beeing greene, it were much better then otherwiſe, but becauſe that is not poſſible, therefore a man muſt helpe himſelfe with ſuch as he can gette, but this is a thing to bee wondered at, that there ſhould be ſuch vertue in a dry ſticke, to expell the matter of the Pocks, yea it is almoſt incredible, but that we ſee the experience of it dailie in diuers perſons, of all manner of complexions, ſo that we are enforced to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it becauſe we ſée it.</p>
               <p>Further you ſhall vnderſtande that, that Woode is beſt which is of middle age, which age muſt be vnderſtoode of the growth, becauſe the young Trees are not yet come to theyr perfection, and the olde Trees are decayed, and therfore it is neceſſarie to chooſe that which is of middle age, and that as greene as is poſſible with the barke vpon it, there is yet one thing more to be obſerued, and that is this, the place where it groweth, this and ſuch like a man muſt know of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which bring it ouer. For that which groweth in S. <hi>Dominicus</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, is not good for this purpoſe, for in hote and dry complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions it is very hurtfull, becauſe of the heate and dryth of the Country where it groweth, which maketh it much hoter and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9025:21"/>dryer then that which groweth els where, as in S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Iland, for the Iland of S. <hi>Dominicus</hi> lieth right vnder the Equinoctiall line, by reaſon whereof, the inhabitants are greatlie troubled with heate, and alſo the fruites of it, are much hoter then in other Countries, but the beſt Woode is found in the Ilande of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> béeing not ſo hote and dry as that of S. <hi>Dominicus,</hi> and may therefore be vſed with leſſer daunger, in hote and drie diſeaſes, as hoarſeneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voice, with ſhortnes of breath called <hi>Aſthma,</hi> and in a conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on called <hi>Ptiſis,</hi> theſe may well be cured with the woode of S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Iland, which were not good to be attempted wyth that of S. <hi>Dominicus</hi> Ilande, becauſe the Patient might therby be brought to a greater drith, and in the end to death. For though there be ſome kind of men, ſo colde and moiſt of complexion, that they might better be cured with the woode of S. <hi>Dominicus</hi> Iland, then with that of S. <hi>Iohns,</hi> yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding there are verie fewe of them, and of thoſe that are hote and drie, or at the leaſt wiſe hote and moiſt, there are manie moe, for that thoſe which are moſt troubled with this diſeaſe, are for the moſt part young women, and young men, and are for the moſt part not ſo colde of nature as they ſhould neede ſuch hote Medicines; and cheefely ſuch dry Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, for by reaſon of the great heate they drie vp the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall moiſture, and thereby ſhorten the life of the Patient, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wood of S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Iland a man may vſe without feare, in hote and drie diſeaſes, béeing prepared accordinglie in the ſeething, and alſo in colde and moiſt diſeaſes béeing prepared thereafter, for it is not ſo much drying as the other, and is notwithſtanding as excellent in colde diſeaſes as any other can be. For the Iland of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> lieth different from the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall line, almoſt eyght degrees, béeing in ſuch ſorte moiſtened with ſprings and Riuers, that the fruites therof are much more excellent, &amp; more natural then are the fruites of the other Iland. In what manner this wood muſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, ſhall heereafter be ſhewed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:9025:22"/>
               <head>Capit. 3. Howe to prepare the Drinke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing we haue alreadie ſhewed you what wood is to be vſed in this Drinke, we will nowe ſhewe you the making or ſeething of it. I haue ſeene the Phiſitians vſe thys drinke almoſt in all diſeaſes, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all men, after one kind of order, but in ſo dooing, whether they did well or not, I leaue to your conſideration. For how can a Shoomaker make euery mans ſhooes vppon one laſt, euen ſo is it with this drinke, which hath cauſed me greatlie to wonder, ſo ſee that it hath been ſo doone by almoſt all Phiſitians. For howe is it poſſible for a man to finde any one thing, which being miniſtred after one kinde of order, ſhoulde cure all kinde of diſeaſes, conſidering how contrarie one diſeaſe is to another.</p>
               <p>But in that we haue héeretofore ſaid of this wood, that it may be vſed in colde, and hote, moiſt, and dry complexions, that is thus to be vnderſtoode. It may be ſo prepared in the ſéething, that in hote diſeaſes it may be a cooling Medicine, and it may alſo be prepared to be a hote Medicine in colde and Melancholicke diſeaſes, and to cure them all perfectlie. Therefore when it is to be miniſtred in hote and dry diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and complexions, it muſt be ſodden with greater quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of water, then when it is to be vſed in cold and moiſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and the diſeaſe by reaſon of the moiſture and coldneſſe of the water, ſhall be made temperate, and by the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vertue which ſecretlie lieth hidden in the woode, it ſhall be perfectlie cured.</p>
               <p>For in this wood is contained a certaine ſecrete or hidden vertue, in curing diſeaſes not alonelie the Pocks, but in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner all diſeaſes: expelling by the vrine and the ſweat, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9025:22"/>is hurtfull or contrarie to nature, therefore you muſt dilligently conſider the nature of the diſeaſe, whether it be hote or cold, that you may make your drinke accordinglie, for in cold diſeaſes, you muſt vſe more wood and leſſe water the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hote diſeaſes, and ſometimes you muſt vſe wine, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times not, and ſometimes the drinke muſt be made of the woode alone, and ſometimes with other additions, as you ſhall heare more at large héereafter.</p>
               <p>Nowe I will teach you howe to ſéeth or prepare your drinke, after a better and more perfect order, then of manie hath hetherto béene vſed, which is after this manner. You ſhall take of the woode, béeing made as ſmall as is poſſible, and put it into a ſtone Pot, which muſt be ſo bigge, that it may not be more then halfe full, when your woode with the other receipts appertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the diſeaſe, are put into it, your receipts therefore beeing put into the Pot, you ſhall ſet it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the fire to ſeeth in a Kettle with water, and (becauſe it ſhall not in ſéething looſe anie of his vertue) you ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtoppe the Pottes mouth ſo cloſe, that no ayre doo iſſue out, for if it get vent that the ayre come foorth, it doth loſe of his vertue, and is ſo much the worſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore you muſt vſe great dilligence in the ſtopping of it, for that is principallie heerein required, and being cloſe ſtopped, you ſhall ſette it to ſeeth in a Kettle of water, bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſo in the Kettle that it fall not, and then make it ſéeth, keeping the Kettle continuallie ſo full of water, that it may alwaies be higher then that which is in the Pot. In this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you ſhall keepe it ſéething at the leaſt tenne howres, but peraduenture you will thinke that it cannot ſéeth, becauſe it is ſo cloſe ſtopped and hath no vent, but that is not materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, for our deſire is, that it ſhould boile or ſéeth without wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loping, for ſeething in this manner, it retaineth all his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, whereby it ſhall performe his operation in better order then he hath doone heretofore, béeing ſimplie ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fire to ſéeth with a couer of wood or ſtone. Moreouer, it may bée you will thinke, that if it be ſtopped as aforeſaide, it may as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9025:23"/>well be ſette vppon the fire to ſéeth, as in a Kettle of water, but heerein you ſhould be deceiued, for béeing ſet vppon the fire to ſeeth in that order, it will rather burſt in peeces then ſeeth, and therefore the beſt way is to ſette it in water as is aforeſaide. For as the water ſeetheth in the the Kittle, ſo ſhall that alſo ſeeth which is in the Pot, although you do not perceiue it to mooue or wallop, which is by reaſon of the cloſe ſtopping, and that it can gette no vent, yet notwithſtanding it dooth ſeeth although it doo not wallop, and by this ſtill ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; doth retaine or rather increaſe in vertue, much more then if it had walloped.</p>
               <p>To prooue the experience heereof, you may take a Hen or ſome other peece of meate, and put it into a Potte, and as much liquor as you meane to haue broth, and ſtoppe the ſaid Potte, ſetting it to ſeeth in a Kettle of water, as aforeſaide, letting it ſéeth in that order, as long as you vſe ordinarily to ſeeth your meate, and you ſhall find it will be as tender, as if it had ſodden &amp; walloped with great force in an open Pot. This is excellent for all ſorts of men in all kinds of diſeaſes, to haue their meate dreſſed in this kind of order, as ſhall be ſhewed more at large, when wee ſhall come to deſcribe the diet of the Patient.</p>
               <p>Thus we haue ſhewed you in what order you ſhall ſeeth this drinke, hereafter when we ſhall ſay, you ſhal take thus much, or ſo much of the woode, and ſhall ſeeth it as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: you ſhall vnderſtand it of this manner of ſéething, and none other, becauſe that this manner is of all other the beſt, howe good ſoeuer they he. The quantitie howe much of each thing ſhall be taken, is ſhewed more at large in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters following, where the drinke ſhall be appointed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the nature of the diſeaſe. Thus much concerning the preparing of the Drinke. Nowe followeth the regiment of the Patient in his diet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:9025:23"/>
               <head>Capit. 4. VVhat regiment the Patient is to obſerue.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt and formoſt you muſt take diligent heede that you doo not pinche your Patient w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> much hunger, but let him haue as much as ſhall be ſufficient to quench hunger with, for hunger doth weaken and pull down a man more then anie other thing, drying vppe the naturall moiſture, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhing the naturall heate, whereby the life of man is ſhortened. For when a man hath kept a verie ſtrait diet, and beene greatlie pinched with hunger a great time, the ſaide time beeing expired, and that he commeth to eate his fill, all his nouriſhment turneth to a certaine wateriſh humor, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the Dropſie &amp; ſuch like foule diſeaſes, the cauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is, that his nouriſhment is giuen him too late. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, a flower which hath beene long parched with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heate of the Sunne, in the ende commeth a raine, which raine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the flower to no other end but to ſpoile and rot it the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the reaſon is, becauſe the raine came too late. Euen ſo is it with a man hauing béene long pined with hunger, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſhall cauſe him to abſtaine, not from that which is good, but from that which is naught, according as hath béen taught in the other Chapters before.</p>
               <p>The beſt and wholeſome meate that you can giue your Patient, is Mutton, Veale, and Hennes, which ſhalbe boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in a Potte ſtopped cloſe, and ſette in a Kettle of water to ſeeth, as is ſhewed before, and hee ſhall not eate his meate freſh, that is to ſay without ſalt, as hath heeretofore beene taught by certaine Doctors, but it ſhall be ſeaſoned in ſuch reaſonable ſort, that it be neither too freſh nor too ſalt, but that it may haue a pleaſant taſte. The reaſon why we allow
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9025:24"/>of ſalt is ſhewed, as we haue ſet downe in another Chapter before, and therefore not to be repeated now for anoiding of tediouſnes. The quantitie of meat and drinke to be vſed by the Patient, cannot well be deſcribed, for that mens ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes are not all alike, the one eating more, and the other leſſe, therefore you ſhall giue the Patient ſo much as ſhall be ſufficient for him to ſuffiſe hunger, taking heede that hée doe not gorge or glut himſelfe, but that he doe alwaies leaue off with an appetite, and concerning his drinke, that ſhall bee ſuch as is appertinent to the diſeaſe, whereof he may drinke as much as him liſteth, beeing alwaies made warme ere hée drinke it, but if he chaunce to be féeble or faint, you ſhal not giue him of his drinke alone at meales, but you ſhall giue him ſome wine with it, eyther Reniſh, or ſmall white wine, mingling the ſame with his drinke, halfe one, halfe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but as for Beere (howe good ſo euer it be) hee ſhall not drinke anie, vntill he be perfectlie cured, becauſe it is hurtful for him.</p>
               <p>In this aforeſaid order you ſhall diet all your Patients, olde and young, to wit, with ſuch good meate dreſſed in this order, vntill they find the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues reaſonably ſatiſ-fied, alwaies leauing with a little appetite, that the Medicine be not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in his operation with ouer much meate. Concerning the obſeruation of the time, you ſhall beginne with the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient in the morning at fiue of the clock, giuing him then his Medicine to drinke, which being doone, you ſhall couer him ſo warme that he may ſweat verie well, he ſhall lie ſtill and ſweat at the leaſt two houres, if he be able to endure ſo long) and you ſhall giue him warme cleane clothes, to dry of the ſweat from his bodie, and you ſhall take away his wet ſhirt, giuing him a dry one well warmed to put on, then hee ſhall put on his clothes, and ſitte by a good fire, and make him readie, and when hee is ready, let him walke vp and downe the Chamber till eyght of the clocke, and then he ſhall goe to dinner, he ſhall firſt ſuppe of the broth with a little Breade, and then eate of the fleſh as much as ſhall ſuffiſe him, as is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:9025:24"/>aforeſaid. After he hath thus dined, he ſhall walke vppe and downe the Chamber recreating himſelfe with ſome paſtime or other to driue awaie Melancholie, till about foure of the clocke in the afternoone, and then he ſhall goe to ſupper, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelfe as at dinner, after which hee ſhall faſt till ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the clocke, then he ſhall goe to bedde, then giue him of his drinke as much as in the morning, to wit, at each time eyght ounces, whereupon you ſhall cauſe him to ſweat, dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſweat from him as you did in the morning, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallie you muſt drie his head well, and his ſhirt which hée put of in the morning you ſhall drie it verie wel, and let him put it on againe warme, and then you ſhall make his bedde with a payre of cleane warme ſheetes, and ſo let him goe to bedde, and let him reſt quietlie till fiue of the clocke the next morning. And then you ſhall giue him his drinke, vſing him in all things as is aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>In this manner (with ſweating and diet) you ſhall vſe all thoſe which may keepe their Chamber in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of their curing: but as for thoſe that muſt goe abroade, their drinke muſt be prepared with wine, as ſhall be ſhewed heereafter, and as for their ſweating and their diet, it muſt be in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects as the other, which béeing performed, they may goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their buſines, although it were better and more ſure for them to tarrie within doores, and that cheefelie in foule, rainie, or bluſtering wether, for although the wine doo reſiſt the contagion of the ayre, yet it cannot reſiſt all, eſpeciallie, when the wether is ſo vntemperate, notwithſtanding, I haue in this maner aforeſaid cured many that went abroad, but yet I counſaile you to cauſe your Patient to tarrie at home in his Chamber by the fire in fouls wether.</p>
               <p>The beſt time to take in hand to cure the Patient, is the Harueſt and the ſpring time, and next to that is the winter, but the Sommer is not good, principallie for hote Cholle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke perſons, for in it ſelfe it is contrarie vnto them by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the great heate and drith, which it increaſeth ſo much the more in them: but to colde, moiſte, and flegmaticke bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:9025:25"/>the Sommer is not ſo hurtfull as to the chollerick, and therefore in time of neede, ſuch Patients may be cured in the Sommer.</p>
               <p>Thus much concerning ſweating, with the time, and the ordering of the diet, nowe followeth the order of curing, and firſt of the great intollerable paine in the heade, which happeneth often in this diſeaſe, ſuffering the Patient not to take any reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. 5. Of the great paine in the head, which taketh away the ſleepe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His intollerable paine is called <hi>Cephalea,</hi> or <hi>Hemicrauea,</hi> and is ſo great and ſo vehement aboue the eyes, that oftentimes the Patient is like to runne madde therewith, &amp; although many meanes be vſed, yet the paine decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not. To cure this and ſuch like paines in the heade, you muſt firſt conſider the complexion of the Patient, whether be be chollerick, phlegmatick, melancholick, or ſanguine, which you ſhall know in this ſort.</p>
               <p>If the Patient be chollericke, his vrine is verie yellowe coloured, and the paine is ſharper vpon the right ſide of the head then in other places, he is leane of bodie and his mouth is commonlie bitter. If he be ſanguine, he is ſomewhat fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of bodie, but not much, and hath a ſweete mouth, his v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine is alſo verie much coloured, and thicke. The phlegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke is commonlie fat, and groſſe of bodie, and ſlow, his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is white and thicke. The mellancholicke are leane and withered, or dry, and beauie ſpirited, enuious, and angrie, wiſhing well to no man, his vrine is bleake and thin, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner like water, and he is alwaies ſad.</p>
               <p>Hauing taught you to knowe the complexion of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:9025:25"/>we will teach you the preparing of each of their Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines ſeuerallie. And firſt of the Chollericke and the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine, becauſe in this they doo agree, to wit, in heat, although the Chollericke man be much dryer then the Sanguine, yet becauſe they are both hote, we will conclude them bothe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one cure, which ſhall be in this order.</p>
               <p>Firſt you ſhall take <hi>Diacarthami,</hi> and <hi>Diaphenicon,</hi> of each three drammes, this you ſhall breake and mingle toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Fewmetorie water, that it may be a drink, which you ſhall giue the Patient to drinke at foure of the clocke in the morning warme, and ſuffer him not to ſleepe, to eate, nor to drinke, till ſuch time as it haue doone working, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhall expell part of the matter (whereof the diſeaſe groweth) by ſiege, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame day you ſhal cheriſh him wel with good meates, ſuch as are before ſhewed for his diet, béeing dreſſed after the aforeſaid order. The next day you ſhal giue him of this drink following, eyght ounces, the drinke is this. You ſhall take of the beſt wood that you can gette (being broken as ſmal as is poſſible) halfe a pound, of cléere ſpring water eight pound, this you muſt ſeeth as is taught in the thirde Chapter, and giue the Patient thereof to drinke morning and euening, at each time eyght ounces, cauſing him to ſweate in ſuch order as before is ſhewed.</p>
               <p>But if ſo be that the Patient cannot keepe within doores but muſt goe abroade about his buſines, you ſhall then make his drinke of halfe wine, halfe water, taking foure poundes of vach, but in ſéething your drinke with wine, yee muſt ſee that the Pot be very cloſelie ſtopped, becauſe the wine is of ſuch a ſubtile and piercing nature, ſo that if it once get anie vent, the vertue of it flieth away. Your drinke béeing thus prepared with Wine, may well be miniſtred to ſuch Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents as cannot keepe at home but muſt goe abroade, but yet in verie foule wether they muſt tarrie at home, and in faire wether they may goe abroade about their buſines, after ſuch time as they haue ſweat and taken their diet as aforeſaide. In this ſort are all ſuch Patients to be vſed (for the paine in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:9025:26"/>the head) as are hote of complexion, the ſpace of eight daies, vntill the ninth day earlie in the morning, at which time you ſhall giue him the aforeſaide Purgation, kéeping him from ſleepe, from meate, and drink, till the Purgation haue doone working, and that the Patient feele no more paine or gréefe in his bellie, and then you ſhall giue him his diet, the ſame day neither in the morning nor the euening ſhall hee drinke any drinke, but onelie the Purgation, except at his meales you may giue him of his drinke, mingling the ſame wyth wine, halfe one, halfe another.</p>
               <p>In the morning he ſhall againe drinke of his drinke, and doe in all reſpects as I haue taught you before, vntill eyght dayes more be expired, and vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ninth day you ſhal purge him againe, and then he ſhall drinke againe as is aforeſaid, in this order he ſhal continue vntill he be whole, and that the paine haue cleane forſaken him. This aforeſaid drinke dooth excellentlie helpe hote and dry complexions by cooling them, and is contrarie to ſuch diſeaſes as are of nature colde &amp; drye, expelling them.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>The curing of the paines in the head of thoſe that are Phlegmatick, and Mellancholick.</head>
                  <p>THe drinke for the Phlegmatick or Mellancholick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, muſt in operation be warmer and dryer then that aforeſaid, and muſt therfore be made in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Take of the wood three quarters of a pounde, bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing broken as ſmall as is poſſible, with ſixe pound of water, and as much Wine, and put it in a ſtone Pot, and béeing ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie cloſe ſtopped, ſette it to ſeeth tenne howres in a Kettle of water as is aforeſaid, whereof the Patient ſhall drink mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening eyght ounces at a time, and at the ende of eyght daies, you ſhall purge him with the aforeſaid Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vſing him in all points as is aforeſaid, with ſweating,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:9025:26"/>and otherwiſe, and he ſhall vndoubtedly be cured. But you muſt haue great regard in ſweating, that you dry his heade well, for that ſhall much further his health. And heere you ſhall vnderſtand, that the paine doth commonlie increaſe til it be at the ſtrongeſt, and then it euery day decreaſeth till at the laſt he feele it no more, therefore you ſhall not be diſmaid though the paine increaſe in the cure, for that commeth to paſſe by the ſtrength of the drink, and it is a very good ſigne, therefore let not the Patient be diſcomfited, but let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, becauſe it is a certaine ſigne of health.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. vj. Of madneſſe or idleneſſe of the head, called Inſania.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His idlenes or madneſſe in the head, called in Latine <hi>Inſania,</hi> proceedeth of a certaine veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous humour or dampe, aſcending from the ſtomacke and the Liuer into the braines, and becauſe the braines through the infection of the Pockes, or ſome ſuch like cauſe is become weake and tender, they are not able to repell or driue backe the ſayde dampe or humour, but remaine vanquiſhed and ouercome of the ſame in ſuch ſort, that they forget to doo their office, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quite out of order, ſo that the Patient hath no rule of him ſelfe, but dooth and ſpeaketh he knoweth not what.</p>
               <p>To cure this diſeaſe, as well that which proceedeth of the Pockes as otherwiſe, (excepting onelie when it commeth of or with a hote ſharpe Ague, becauſe therein is great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death) you may doo it with the drinke made of thys Wood, without any impediment: which muſt be prepared after this manner, for ſuch as are hote of complexion, as the Chollericke and Sanguine are. Take of this Wood, beeing made very ſmall, one pounde, fayre water eyght poundes,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:9025:27"/>which you muſt ſeeth as is aforeſaide, and giue him thereof euery morning and euening eyght ounces, at a time &amp; cauſe him to ſweat well, and you muſt dry the ſweat fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his head verie well, becauſe the diſenſe lyeth altogether in the heade. His diet and his drinke ſhall be as is mencioned in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapter, notwithſtanding as litle as may be, for in this diſeaſe much meate is very hurtfull, and therfore he muſt be content with a little, hee muſt drinke no Wine, for that it is contrarie both to his diſeaſe and complexion, becauſe it aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vp into the head, he muſt drinke of his drinke alone as much as he will, &amp; it muſt alwaies be a little warme. Thus dooing, he ſhall without doubt be cured by Gods helpe.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>The Phlegmatick and the Mellancholicke muſt be thus cured.</head>
                  <p>TAke of this Wood one pound, of Water foure pound, of Wine two pounde, this you muſt ſeeth as is aforeſaide, and giue him thereof euery day to drinke morning and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning eyght ounces at a time, continuing the ſame vntill hee be cured. And although in the beginning the Wine doe him no good, yet you ſhall not leaue to vſe the ſame ſtill in hys drinke, for that it is a notable Medicine for his complexion, béeing meaſurablie vſed, and therefore you ſhall ſeeth him his drinke as aforeſaid, and it ſhall in the end perfectly help him.</p>
                  <p>You may giue theſe Patients leſſe meate then the Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lericke or Sanguine, yet you ſhal not famiſh them, and that principallie the Mellancholicke, and hee ſhall alſo not ſweat ſo long as thoſe that are moiſt of complexion, becauſe hee is drie, yet he muſt ſweat at the leaſt an howre and a halfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Phlegmaticke to ſweat much more if he be able to endure it, becauſe that of his owne complexion hee is verie moyſt, and yet much more moiſt by reaſon of his diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:9025:27"/>
Therefore it is verie good for him to ſweats, becauſe it dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vp all ſuch ouerplus moiſtnes, and in the ende reſtoreth him to his health and his vnderſtanding, and driueth awais all nodes or tumors vpon his heade, if he haue any, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen fores in any place of the bodie, ſhall by vertue of thys drink be healed within the fortie daies, and therefore let him not refuſe to vſe it.</p>
                  <p>Héere is to be obſerued, that ſuch Patients as are idle headed, ſhall not in any wiſe goe abroade, till ſuch time as they are perfectlie cured, but ſhall remaine at home in their Chamber, keeping them as quiet as is poſſible, for reſt is very good and profitable for them. If you obſerue this order before ſhewed, the Patient ſhall vndoubtedlie be cured if God will.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. 7. Of the Falling-ſickneſſe, called in Latine Epileptia.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His diſeaſe ſpringeth of ouermuch moyſture in the braine, wherethrough at certain times the braines béeing troubled, there chaunceth vnto them a certaine obſtruction; by meanes whereof, the Patient is bereft of the ſtrength of his ſinnewes, and ſo falleth to the ground. And according to the ſcituation of the place which the diſeaſe occupieth, ſo the accidents doo manifeſt themſelues, as ſometimes wyth contraction, that is, in plucking of the ioynts, and ſomtimes in foming at the mouth, with barking and other ſuch vnſéem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie geſtures.</p>
               <p>But peraduenture it will cauſe ſome to meruaile greatly that I ſhould teach the curing of ſuch a hard diſeaſe, with a Drinke made of this <hi>Lignum Guaiacum,</hi> yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe I haue learned the ſame by experience, &amp; haue
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9025:28"/>therewith cured moe then tenne Patients, I will therefore publiſh the ſame for the commoditie of all, that ſuch as are therwith troubled, may haue recourſe hereto in time of néed and find remedie for the ſame, which by the helpe of GOD they ſhall vndoubtedlie obtaine, (though they had had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide diſeaſe tenne yeeres together) following the order héere ſette downe, which is this. You ſhall vſe nothing but onelie this drinke following, purging the Patient in ſuch order as I ſhall teache you.</p>
               <p>Firſt for the Chollericke and Sanguine complexion, you ſhall take of the ſaid Wood halfe a pound, fayre water eyght poundes, this you muſt ſeeth in ſuch order as is ſhewed in the thirde Chapter before: and you ſhall giue the Patient thereof euery morning and euening eyght ounces at a time, and ſhal cauſe him to ſweat verie wel, for it is excellent good for him, &amp; hauing drunke therof eyght dayes, you ſhall purge him with this Purgation: Take of <hi>Hiera picra galeni,</hi> halfe an ounce, <hi>Diacarthami</hi> three drams, and beate amongſt it of <hi>Epirimi,</hi> and <hi>Agarici trociſtati</hi> of each two drammes, this you muſt mingle with <hi>Betoni</hi> water, and <hi>Cuſcuta</hi> Water, putting thereto ſo much water, that it may be a Potion, this the Patient muſt drink at foure of the clocke in the morning, he muſt neither ſleepe, eate, nor drinke, vntill the Medicine haue doone working, and that he feele no more pain or rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in his bellie. Then you ſhall giue him his diet, and the ſame day he ſhall not drinke, but at his meales according as he is wont to doo, the next morning he ſhall beginne againe with his drinke, dooing in all reſpects as hee did the eyght daies before, with ſweating and otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>This order you ſhall in all points obſerue, vntill fortie dayes be expired, purging the Patient euery eyght or ninth day once. But this is alwaies to be noted, as well in thys Chapter as in all the other, that when you begin your cure, the firſt day the Patient muſt be purged, with the Purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mencioned in the ſaid Chapter, and then to procéed in ſuch ſort as is there ſpecified, continuing the cure as I ſaid before,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:9025:28"/>the ſpace of fortie dayes. For though in this maner aforeſaid I once cured a Woman of this greeuous diſeaſe, within fiue and twentie daies, yet I would wiſh the cure to be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fortie daies, that you may be the more aſſured y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhould not returne againe.</p>
               <p>In this foreſaide order you may cure all kindes of lame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in hote and dry complexions, and alſo all lameneſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of the Palſie, though it procéeded not of the Pockes, but of the influence of the ſtarres, or the conſtellation of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> and the Moone in his birth, as Aſtronomie teacheth. Theſe and all other lameneſſe whatſoeuer, may in Cholle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke perſons be cured in the aforeſaid manner, without all imperfection, of howe long continuaunce ſoeuer they haue beene. In his diet he muſt behaue himſelfe meſurablie, leaſt any Ague or other accident doo happen vnto him, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his health would be farre to ſeeke, for which cauſe, ſobrietie in his diet is very requiſit. This is ſufficient concerning Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick and Sanguine complexions.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>The curing of the falling ſickeneſſe in Phlegmaticke and Mellancholie perſons.</head>
                  <p>FOr theſe, the Drinke muſt be made more warming and drying then in other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plexions, the making of it is thus. Take one pound of this Woode, with fiue pounds of water, and three pound of good Wine, this muſt be ſodden as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, being ſtopped verie cloſe, and you muſt giue the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient thereof euery morning and euening ſeauen or eyght ounces at a time, obſeruing the ſame the ſpace of eight daies, vpon the ninth day you ſhall purge him with the aforeſaide Purgation, vſing him in all points as is aforeſaid of the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick perſons, excepting onely in his drinke, which muſt be made as is aboue ſaid, to be more warming and drying then the other. Thus much concerning ſuch diſeaſes as ſpring vp in the braines.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:9025:29"/>
               <head>Capit. 8. Of Polipus an ill diſeaſe in the noſe, whereof commeth the Cancer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Olipus</hi> is a certaine fleſhie Apoſtemation growing in the noſe, conuerting it ſelfe at laſt to a Cancer, the cure thereof is not long to be protracted, for if it be let runne to a Cancer, it is ſo much the harder to be cured. Therefore the Patient muſt thus be purged, foure daies together you muſt giue him this Iulep or Sirop.</p>
               <p>Take of Sirope <hi>De fumo terre,</hi> one ounce, Sirope <hi>De cicorea,</hi> two ounces, Burrage water, Endiue water, Cicore water, <hi>Fumiterre</hi> water, of each two ounces, this hee muſt drinke at foure times: vppon the fift day you ſhall giue him this Purgation. You ſhall take <hi>Confectionis Hamech,</hi> and <hi>Electuarij, De ſuco roſarum,</hi> of each three drams, this you ſhall giue him with Burrage water, and <hi>Fumiterre</hi> water, vſing ſo much of the ſaid water that it may be a drink, which you ſhall giue him to drinke at fiue of the clocke in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſuffering him neither to ſleepe, to eate nor to drink, til the Purgation haue doone working, and that the Patient do not feele any more rumbling or paine in his bellie, and then let him eate meaſurablie. Then for the Chollericke perſons, you ſhall make this drinke following, giuing him thereof e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day morning and euening eyght ounces at a time, and whyle he is drinking of it, you ſhall with an Inſtrument cut away the ſuperfluous fleſh out of his noſe, as much as ſhalbe requiſite, cauſing him once euery houre to clenſe his noſe with a little ſticke wet in Honie of Roſes, and hauing drunk of his drinke eyght dayes together, you ſhall purge him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with the aforeſaid Purgation. This is the Drinke.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:9025:29"/>
Take of the Wood halfe a pound, and of water eyght pound, this you muſt ſéeth as aforeſaid, and giue it to the Chollerick perſon to drinke, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>For the Phlegmatick and the Mellan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholicke, it muſt be prepared thus.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the Wood a pound and a halfe, <hi>Angelica</hi> and <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingale</hi> of each one ounce, of water ſeauen pounde, of Wine three pound. This muſt be ſtopped verie cloſe, and ſodden as aforeſaid, giuing thereof to the colde and moyſte of complexion, euery morning and euening eyght ounces at a time, purging him euery ninth day with the aforeſaid Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, he ſhall alſo waſhe his noſe with the Drinke, for it digeſteth, clenſeth, and healeth aboue meaſure, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhall often waſh and clenſe his noſe therewith, and in ſo dooing, he ſhall vndoubtedly in ſhort time be healed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. ix. Of shortnes of vvinde, coughes, and ſtuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finges in the breaſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the Chollericke and the Sanguine, you ſhall make this drinke following. Take of the Woode three quarters of a pound, Iſope a handfull, Dates a quarter of a pound, Lyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris two ounces, this muſt be ſodden in tenne pounds of water, as in the third Chapter, and the day before he beginne to drinke thereof, you ſhall giue him this Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Take <hi>Electuarij inde maioris</hi> halfe an ounce, put there to <hi>Agarici trociſcati,</hi> three drammes, giue it him to drinke with Bugloſſe water, the next day giue him of the aforeſaid
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:9025:30"/>drink morning and euening, ſixe ounces at a time, vſing him with ſweating, dyet and drinke as is aforeſayd, and purging him with the ſaid Purgation euery ninth day, and he ſhal be healed in a ſhort ſpace, and ſhall be as long winded as euer he was in his life.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>The drinke for the Phlegmatick and the Mellancholick.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the Woode one pound, Iſope and Dates, of each a handfull, <hi>Agarici trociſcati</hi> two drammes, water fiue pounde, ſweete Wine fiue pounde, ſeeth it as is aforeſaide, beeing very cloſe ſtopped, and giue the Patient thereof to drinke morning and euening eyght ounces at a time, dooing as is aforeſayd. But for his ordinarie drinke at his meales, you ſhall make him this that followeth, (for he may not vſe other at his meales becauſe of the Agaricke.) Take of the Wood one pound, Iſope, Dates, of each a handfull, Lycoris two ounces, water ſixe pound, ſweete Wine three pounde, this ſhall he drinke at meales, in all other reſpects as in diet, ſweating, purging, and ſuch like, you ſhall vſe him as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and he ſhall by Gods helpe be cured. Although this diſeaſe ſometimes be ſomewhat long in curing, yet you néede not feare, for in the ende it ſhall vndoubtedly by Gods helpe be cured, though the Patient haue had it neuer ſo long time.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. 10. Of the diſeaſes in the ſtomacke, as paines, queſines, vomiting, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>THeſe diſeaſes doo ariſe of aboundaunce of cold, phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticke, and moiſt humors, and ſometimes of blacke choller or mellancholie, to cure theſe diſeaſes, you muſt firſt prepare the matter with this Drinke, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:9025:30"/>after purge the Patient. Take of Mintes, Wormewood, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſope, Betonie, Bugloſſe, Cicorey, Lettice, of each a handful, Senne leaues, and <hi>Polipodium,</hi> of each two ounces, thys muſt be ſodden as aforeſaid with a pint of water, giuing the Patient thereof to drinke euery morning ſixe ounces, till it be drunke out, then you ſhall purge him with <hi>Benedicta lax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atiua,</hi> and <hi>Stomaticom luxatium,</hi> of each thrée drams, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereto thrée ounces of Wormewood water, and giue it the Patient warme to drinke, kéeping himſelfe as I haue ſhewed in other Chapters before. The ſame day y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, he ſhall neither eate much, nor any groſſe meate, nor drinke much at his meales, and at the end of his meale you ſhall giue him a ſlice of <hi>Diacitron,</hi> for that dooth comfort the ſtomacke excellentlie, and the next daie you ſhall giue him this drinke.</p>
               <p>Take of the Wood halfe a pound, water ſixe pound, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>core and Borage of each a handfull, this you ſhall ſéeth as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaide, giuing the Patient thereof morning and euening ſixe ounces at a time, purging him euery ninth day once with the aforeſaid Purgation, and the ſame day that he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, you ſhall giue him after his dinner one ſlice of <hi>Diacitro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> obſeruing this, he ſhall vndoubtedlie be cured.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>For the Phlegmatick and the Mellan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholick, how he is to be cured.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt you ſhall make him this drinke to prepare the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter withall. Take Sage, Iſope, Margerome &amp; Mints, of each a handfull, <hi>Cardus benedictus,</hi> Sorrell and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diue, of each a handfull and a halfe, <hi>Polipodij</hi> thrée oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Rhabarbe</hi> halfe an ounce, this you muſt ſéeth as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, with a pint of Wine, and a pint of Water, giuing the Patient therof euery morning ſixe ounces vntill it be drunk vppe. Then giue him this Purgation, <hi>Electuarij,</hi> Eleſcoph
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:9025:31"/>halfe an ounce, <hi>Agarici trociſcati, Rhabarbari</hi> of each a dram, and a halfe, breake and mingle them in two ounces of wine, and two ounces of Betonie water. This you ſhall giue him in the morning at foure of the clocke, and at noone after his meate you ſhall giue him a ſlice of <hi>Diacitron,</hi> and let him not drinke vpon it, afterward you ſhall giue him this drinke fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
                  <p>Take of the Wood twelue ounces, Minte and Anis ſéedes of each a handful, water foure pounde, wine thrée pounde, let it ſeeth as aforeſaid béeing cloſe ſtopped, and giue the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient thereof euery morning and euening eyght ounces at a time, purging him once euery day with the aforeſaid Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and he ſhall be cured of all diſeaſes of the ſtomack howe ill ſoeuer they be.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. 11. Of diſeaſes of the Liuer, as obſtruction Apoſteme and the Dropſie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll the diſeaſes of the Liuer (as ſtopping, hardneſſe, apoſtemation and the Dropſie) may all be cured with this excellent Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, if ſo be the diſeaſe be not ioyned with a hote Ague, for then it ſhould not be profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but verie hurtfull to vſe it, and therefore in ſuch a caſe you muſt vſe cooling Medicines, vntill the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue be cleane gone, and then you ſhall giue him this drinke. Take Agrimonie, Liuerwort, Cicorea, Endiue, Acetoſa, or Sorrell, of each a handfull, Lettice one ounce, Mellon ſeede, Gowrde ſeedes, of each halfe an ounce, <hi>Polipodij</hi> two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Agarici trociſcati,</hi> and <hi>Rhabarbari,</hi> of each thrée drams, this you ſhall ſéeth in a pynt of water, the ſpace of ſixe houres in the aforeſaid order, then take it out, and ſtraine it through a cloth, putting in ſo much Suger that it may be very ſwéet,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:9025:31"/>then put in a little good Wine Vineger. Héereof you ſhall giue the Patient to drinke euerie morning ſixe ounces, vntil it be drunke out. You ſhall not need to giue the Patient any other Purgation, for this ſhall giue him euery day two or thrée ſtooles, and more then that is not good for him, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the tendernes of the Liuer, and vppon his Liuer you ſhall lay a cloth made wette in Agrimonie water, and Cico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rey water, taking dilligent heede in keeping the ſaid cloth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like warme and moiſt, leaſt the cold doo encreaſe the diſeaſe for cold is very hurtfull in Apoſtemations, and therefore you muſt keepe the cloth alwaies warme, when hee hath thus continued foureteene daies, he ſhall then take the drink bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made in this order.</p>
               <p>Take of the Wood eyght ounces, of water tenne pound, Cicorey, Endiue, Agrimonie, Cuſcuta, of each a handfull, Reupontice, Rubarbe of each an ounce, this muſt be ſodden as aforeſaid cloſe ſtopped, and giue the Patient thereof eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morning and euening ſixe ounces at a time, continuing the ſame vntill he be cured. But if he chaunce to be ſo harde bound that hee cannot goe to the ſtoole, then you ſhall euerie ninth day giue him this Purgation.</p>
               <p>Take <hi>Electuarij de ſucco roſarum,</hi> halfe an ounce, put therto <hi>Rhabarbari electi</hi> two drams, make this in forme of a Potion, with Agrimonie water, and giue it him in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at foure of the clocke to drinke, vſing ſuch order therein as I haue preſcribed in other Purgations. But if his drinke doo purge him, then you ſhall not néede any other Purgation for it dooth purge ſufficiently in many Patients. All this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, is to be vnderſtood of the Chollerick and the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine complexions.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>To cure the diſeaſes of the Liuer in Phlegmatick and Mellancholike Patients.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt you ſhall lay vppon the Liuer of the Patient <hi>Empla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum de Melilote,</hi> ſpread vpon white Lether, which ſhall
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:9025:32"/>continue vpon it the ſpare of eyght dayes; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane while he ſhall vſe this drinke. Take Maiden hayre, Wormwood, Betonie, Agrimonie, Cypres, <hi>Fumiterre,</hi> Red Coleworts, of each a handfull, Cuſcuta, Camomill flowres, of each halfe a handfull, Licoris two ounces, <hi>Polipodij</hi> thrée ounces, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne leaues two ounces, <hi>Agarici trociſcati,</hi> halfe an ounce, wine one pound; &amp; water one pound, this muſt be ſodden in a pot, ſtopped very cloſe, as a foreſaid, make it ſweet with Suger, and giue the Patient thereof to drinke euery morning ſixe ounces, vntill it be drunke out. Then giue him this drinke following, taking away the aforeſaide Plaiſter, in the place wherof you muſt lay an Oxicrociu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> playſter, which ſhal there continue vntill ſuch time as you perceiue the Patient to be cured.</p>
                  <p>The drinke is this, take of the Wood one pound, of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fiue pound, and of Wine fiue pounde, put thereto of <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miterre,</hi> Agrimonie, Cypris, of each one handfull, <hi>Polipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dij,</hi> Senne leaues, of each three ounces, <hi>Rhabarbari</hi> halfe an ounce, all this put together, muſt be ſodden as aforeſaide, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Patient thereof to drinke euery morning and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning eyght ounces at a time vntill he be cured: the Patient ſhall not neede any other Purgation for the drink ſhal purge him ſufficientlie, his diet ſhall be young Hennes fleſhe, and ſuch other things as are light of digeſtion, and doo giue much nouriſhment; and he ſhall alſo not eate much, but ſhall be ſo ſpare in his diet, that he ſhall riſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his meales with great hunger, which ſhall helpe greatlie in the curing of thys dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.</p>
                  <p>This foreſaid cure obſerued in all points as is heere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, ſhall not faile you, for I haue had often experience thereof, and haue alwaies had good ſucceſſe: but one thing I muſt warne you of, that is, if there be great heate in the Dropſie, and that the diſeaſe doo originally ſpring of heate, that then you take not in hand to cure it with this drinke of <hi>Lignum Guaiacum,</hi> vnleſſe he be before ſufficientlie cooled, becauſe it will rather increaſe then diminiſh the diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:9025:32"/>
obſeruing the aforeſaid order, you cannot be deceiued, for it is perfect in all the aforenamed diſeaſes of the Liuer.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. 12. Of the diſeaſes of the Mother, as the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous iſſue of menſtrums and to ſtay them, and of barrenneſſe.</head>
               <p>FIrſt for thoſe women that are of Chollericke and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plexion, you ſhall giue them this drinke. Take Fennell, Betonie, of each a handfull, <hi>Polipodij,</hi> Senne leaues, of each three ounces, this muſt be ſodden as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in a pynt of water, giue the Patient thereof euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fiue ounces, vntill it be drunke out, then giue her thys drinke following.</p>
               <p>Take of the Wood one pound, Wine and Water of each ſixe pounds, this muſt be ſodden very cloſe ſtopped as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: giuing the Patient thereof euery morning and euening ſixe ounces at a time, purging her euery ninth day with this Purgation. <hi>Diacobicum turbit,</hi> halfe an ounce, <hi>Mirabola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum Citrinorum, et Indorum,</hi> of each two dramnes, this giue her with <hi>Fumiterre</hi> water, dooing as is aforeſaide the iſſue ſhall ceaſe, but if it doo lacke iſſue, it ſhall heereby ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine iſſue in due time, for by this order of curing, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is wholly renewed, by meanes whereof, all her acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents doe ceaſe. And if by meanes héereof the ſecrete part be infected with any open ſore or otherwiſe, ſhe ſhall with this ſaid drinke waſh the place often, and ſhee ſhall in ſhort ſpace be cured perfectly, both within and without. Let this ſuffiſe for the Chollerick and the Sanguine.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>To cure the diſeaſes of the Mother in the Phlegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick and Mellancholick women.</head>
                  <p>THeſe Patients muſt firſt be purged with this Purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Diapheniconis</hi> halfe an ounce, <hi>Mirabolanorum Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulorum</hi>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:9025:33"/>and <hi>Embelicorum,</hi> of each two drams, then you ſhal ſeeth her this drinke. Take of the Wood a pound and a halfe, of Water ſixe pound, of Wine fiue pound, ſéeth this as afore ſayde, giuing the Patient thereof to drinke euery day mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening, at the leaſt ſixe ounces at a time, purging her euery ninth day with the aforeſaid Purgation, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this order the ſpace of fortie dayes, ſhe ſhall vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be cured, and ſhall be more healthfull then euer ſhee was before.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. 13. To cure the Cancer in any place of the bodie whereſoeuer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His lothſome and fearefull diſeaſe béeing once ſetled, is not cured with any Medicine, and therefore you muſt in time haue recourſe to this excellent remedie, for there haue manie beene cured by meanes of this, which coulde not find helpe by any other. The Patient muſt firſt be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with thys drinke. Take Houndes tongue called in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine <hi>Cinogloſſa,</hi> and Agrimonie, of each two handfuls, Wine halfe a pound, water one pound, <hi>Polipodii</hi> &amp; Senne leaues, of each one dram, <hi>Agarici trociſcati</hi> halfe an ounce, <hi>Elebori nigri</hi> two drammes, thys altogether ſhal be ſodden as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, and then make it ſweete with Suger, &amp; giue the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent thereof to drinke euery morning ſixe ounces, vntill it bee drunke out, then giue him this drinke following. Take of the Wood halfe a pounde, water tenne pounde, Ciuogloſſa, and Agrimonie of each a handfull: ſeeth thys as aforeſaide, and giue the Patient thereof to drinke, euery morning and euening eyght ounces at a time, purging him euery nynth day vntill he be cured, with <hi>Confectio Hamech</hi> halfe an ounce, and if the Patient be ſtrong of bodie, you ſhall gyue
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:9025:33"/>him ſixe drammes with <hi>Fumiterre</hi> water, his meate that hée ſhall eate, ſhall be ſodden in ſuch order as is aforeſaide, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereto Lettice and Bugloſſe, and hee ſhall be ſober in his diet: but if it chaunce the Patient not to be cured in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie daies, yet he ſhall not leaue of the cure vntill ſuch time as hee be whole, for that this is the ſureſt remedie that can be found againſt this lothſome diſeaſe, and therefore I woulde wiſh you not to leaue it vntill you be perfectly cured.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>To cure the Cancer in colde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt you muſt purge the Patient with an ounce of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio Hamech,</hi> mingled with Agrimonie water, this ſhal be giuen him in ſuch order as is vſed in other Purgations. And then you ſhall giue him this drinke following. Take of the wood a pound and a halfe, Water and Wine, of each fiue pound, Agrimonie &amp; Cinogloſſa of each a handfull, this muſt be ſodden as aforeſaid, béeing verie cloſe ſtopped at the leaſt tenne howres, giuing the Patient therof euery morning and euening, eyght ounces at a time, keeping him verie warme that he may ſweat, not forgetting to purge him euery ninth day, with ſixe drams of <hi>Confectio Hamech,</hi> ſo dooing, he ſhall by Gods helpe be cured, although hée had had it ten yeeres.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. 14. Of all other Vlcerations, whether they come of the Pockes or otherwiſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll other Vlcerations whether they procéed of the Pockes or otherwiſe, as Fiſtoles in the Mother, and other open ſores in the ſecrete parts both of man and woman, which cannot with any other Medicine be healed, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:9025:34"/>ſores whereſoeuer, alſo all paine and greefe in the armes and legges, and all puſhes or byles in any place of the bodie, may altogether be cured with the drinke made of this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Wood aforeſaid, after this manner. Firſt you ſhal purge the Patient with <hi>Pillulae Iudae,</hi> giuing him in the euening thrée houres after his ſupper foure ſcruples of the ſaid Pilles in the night when he awaketh, feeling great paine and rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in his bellie, he ſhall prepare himſelfe to the ſtoole, and hauing begunne to purge, he ſhall not ſleepe vntill hee haue doone purging, and that he féele no more griping or rumbling in his bellie, and then he ſhall eate ſome good meat, as Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton or Veale, which muſt be ſodden as heeretofore I haue taught you, then you ſhall giue him this drinke following. Take of the Wood one pound, water twelue pounde, thys muſt be ſodden as aforeſaide, giue the Patient thereof twiſe euery day, eyght ounces at a time, cauſing him to ſweat wel, for that dooth helpe very much in the curing of his diſeaſe, and euery ninth day you ſhall purge him with the ſaid Pils, but in the euening when you giue him the Pilles, you ſhall not ſuffer him to drinke but at his ſupper, this order he muſt obſerue fortie daies.</p>
               <p>But if it come to paſſe (as oftentimes it dooth) that the Patient is ſooner cured, as ſometimes in twentie or fiue and twentie daies, yet I cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſaile you not to leaue of the cure vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the fortie daies be expired, that you may be the more aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that it ſhall not returne againe, for oftentimes it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be cured when the roote remaineth ſtill within, which in the ende breaketh out againe, and ſo is worſe then at the firſt, and therefore I counſaile you to continue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame fortie dayes, that the roote beeing taken away, you need not feare the returne of the diſeaſe.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:9025:34"/>
                  <head>For the Phlegmaticke and the Mellancholicke.</head>
                  <p>YOu ſhall purge the Patient with <hi>Pillulae cochiae,</hi> and <hi>Pillulę Aggregatiuę,</hi> of each two ſcruples, this muſt bee giuen him in the euening, vſing him in all reſpects as is ſaid of the other, then you ſhall giue him this drinke.</p>
                  <p>Take of the Wood a pound and a halfe, wine ſixe pound, Water ſeauen pound, this you muſt ſeeth as aforeſaide, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Patient thereof morning and euening eyght oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at a time, purging him euery ninth day once with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Pilles, cauſing him to ſweat verie well. The ſores he ſhall waſh euery day ſixe or ſeauen times with the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid drinke, for it is the beſt ſalue that can be vſed héerein, for it clenſeth &amp; mollifieth more then any other Oyntment that is vſed, and to conclude, I ſay, if you doo according to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of this Chapter, there is no Malladie ſo ill procéeding of the Pockes, nor other open ſores how ill ſoeuer, but may by this meanes be cured.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>Capit. 15. Hovv to cure the Rupture.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ometimes it happeneth a man firſt to bée broken, and after to gette the Pockes, and ſomtime it chaunceth him to breake while he hath them, theſe cannot any other way be cured, but with the Drinke made of this excellent Woode, the order of it is thus. You ſhall firſt purge him with Pilles <hi>De fumiterrę,</hi> and bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purged you ſhall giue him this drinke following. Take of the Woode one pound, of Water twelue pounde, this you
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:9025:35"/>muſt ſeeth as aforeſaide, and giue the Patient thereof twiſe euery day eyght ounces at a time, purging him euery ninth day once with the aforeſaid Purgation. This he ſhal obſerue fortie daies, and hee ſhall vndoubtedly be cured, though hee were fiftie yeeres olde and had had it twentie yeeres and if he haue the Pockes, they ſhall alſo herewithall be cured, and he ſhall be made whole and ſound in all his members.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>To cure the ſame in Phlegmatick and Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholicke perſons.</head>
                  <p>THeſe muſt firſt be purged with <hi>Pillulis fetidis,</hi> whereof you ſhal giue the Patient foure ſcruples, making therof nine Pilles, which he ſhall take in the euening, as aforeſaid, the next day you ſhal giue him of this drink. Take of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wood, one pound, Wine and water, of each foure pounde, this you muſt ſeeth as aforeſaide, giuing the Patient thereof euerie morning and euening eyght ounces at a time, purging him once euery ninth day with the aforeſaid Pilles. His meate ſhall be ſodden as aforeſaid, with <hi>Sanikell</hi> &amp; <hi>Conſolida Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior,</hi> whereto you ſhall adde Wine and Cinamon to amende the taſte.</p>
                  <p>In this ſort I cured one in the ſpace of a month, which was ſeauentie yeeres old, making him whole and ſound fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all ſuch greefes as he had beſides. Therfore you ſhall not vſe any other meanes, for thoſe that haue the Pocks, and are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo troubled with the rupture, but onely this aforeſaide, for without this, nothing els can helpe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:9025:35"/>
               <head>Capit. xvj. Of Podagra or the Goute.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His diſeaſe is of a wonderfull ſtrange nature as experience teacheth vs, comming to man firſt by the influence of the ſtars in his birth, that is when the Moone is infortuned wyth <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Saturne,</hi> which cauſeth the perſon then borne, to be more inclined to the ſaid diſeaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others are, and then withall, leading his life diſorderly in lecherie, ſurfeiting, and drunkenneſſe, is by and by attached with this ſaid diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>The opinion of many men is, that this diſeaſe cannot be cured, but that is not ſo, for there are very manie that are cured of it, which by their diſordered liuing doo fall into it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, which if they would leade their liues well and in good order, they ſhould remaine whole being once cured, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie thoſe that are healed in this ſort: notwithſtanding, I graunt it will verie hardlie be cured, if it runne ſo farre that it haue hardened the knockles of the hands, and the ioynts of the foote, for then the matter is become ſo dry, that it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible to reſolue it, but if it be taken in any reſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble time, it may in this ſort be cured.</p>
               <p>Firſt you muſt purge the Patient with <hi>Pillule de hermo dactilis,</hi> whereof you ſhall take one dramme, making there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſeauen Pilles, which you ſhall giue the Patient at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, letting him ſleepe thereon three howres, and then you ſhall awake him if he awake not of himſelfe, keeping him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake that the Purgation may the better worke vppon him, not ſuffering him to ſleepe vntill it haue doone working, and then he ſhall eate his meate, the next day you ſhall giue him the drinke mencioned in the former Chapter for the Cholle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, but in the ſéething of it, you ſhall put into it a handfull
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:9025:36"/>of Cipres, which is an Hearbe ſo called, purging him euerie ninth day once with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aforeſaid Pilles, dooing in all reſpects as is mentioned in the Chapter going before: but you ſhall cauſe him to ſweat verie much, for that is verie good and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to dry the ſweat very well from him with warme clothes, that it goe not in againe, for if it goe in againe, it were as good for him not to ſweat at all. Thus much for the Cholle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke and the Sanguine.</p>
               <div type="prescription">
                  <head>For the Phlegmaticke and the Mellancholick.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou ſhall alſo purge him with the aforeſaide Pilles, and then you ſhall giue him of the drinke mentioned in the former Chapter, for the Phlegmaticke and the Mellancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, remembring in the ſeething, to put in a handfull of Cypres, purging him euerie ninth day with the aforeſaide Pilles, which you ſhall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue vntill he be healed.</p>
                  <p>This ſuffiſeth for the Goute, ſhewing the order howe it is to be cured. We haue alſo entreated ſufficiently of all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents which chaunce by meanes of the Pocks, with diuers other diſeaſes, ſpringing not of the Pockes but of other cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, howe all ſuch diſeaſes are to be cured by meanes of this excellent wood, is before ſufficientlie made manifeſt. I haue alſo in the firſt part of this Booke (for their ſakes that haue any vnderſtanding) opened many noble ſecrets of Mercurie, but becauſe the moſt part are not enſtructed in the Arte of preparing the Mercurie, I haue for theyr ſakes written this ſeconde part, for the helpe of the Patient, becauſe I woulde not haue them remaine vncured, wiſhing the health of all men.</p>
                  <p>Yet notwithſtanding, Mercurie beeing rightly prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, dooth ſeeme to worke miracles, ſo ſhort and ſo excellent
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:9025:36"/>hee is in his operation, whereof heereafter (God wylling) wee will wryte more.</p>
                  <p>Thus I conclude this treatiſe, deſiring God to ſpare me vntill I haue performed my purpoſed intent, in writing to his glory and to the profit of my neighbour. Thus louing Reader I commit thee to GOD almightie, to whom bée all prayſe, honour and glorie, both nowe and for euermore, Amen.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed by Iohn Charlwood.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:9025:37"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Faultes eſcaped in the Printing.</head>
            <list>
               <item>PAge <hi>2.</hi> line <hi>3.</hi> put out the firſt and. Page <hi>7,</hi> line <hi>2,</hi> read <hi>Mercurie</hi> and <hi>Lignum vitae.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page <hi>7,</hi> line <hi>9,</hi> for Ciuober, read Cinober.</item>
               <item>Page <hi>8,</hi> line <hi>25,</hi> for Bernagie, read Borrage.</item>
               <item>Page <hi>18,</hi> line <hi>31,</hi> for diſſolue it, reade diſſolue them.</item>
               <item>Page <hi>21,</hi> line <hi>3,</hi> reade <hi>Emunctorij,</hi> line <hi>4.</hi> read places.</item>
               <item>Page <hi>21,</hi> line <hi>30,</hi> for in, read on.</item>
               <item>Page <hi>26,</hi> line <hi>4,</hi> reade <hi>feniculi,</hi> and for <hi>endinie,</hi> read <hi>endiuię</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page <hi>26,</hi> line <hi>13,</hi> for <hi>Iudum,</hi> read <hi>Indum.</hi> and for <hi>Hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dactilus,</hi> read <hi>Hermodactiles.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page <hi>26,</hi> line <hi>15,</hi> read <hi>Arthriticae,</hi> and for <hi>aree,</hi> read <hi>aurae.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page <hi>26,</hi> line <hi>16,</hi> for <hi>ſiue,</hi> read <hi>ſine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page <hi>51,</hi> line <hi>7,</hi> read <hi>ſtomaticum laxatiuum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page <hi>51,</hi> line <hi>13,</hi> read <hi>Dicitonion,</hi> and for <hi>Diacitron,</hi> line <hi>21.</hi> read <hi>Diacitonion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page <hi>52,</hi> line <hi>5,</hi> read <hi>Diacitonion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page <hi>55,</hi> line <hi>18,</hi> for <hi>Diacobicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> turbit,</hi> read <hi>Diacatholicon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page <hi>58,</hi> line <hi>5,</hi> read <hi>Indae.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Alſo I admoniſh the freendlie Reader, to take héed howe he doe miniſter any purgatiue receit, according as it is heere in this Booke ſette foorth, without the good aduiſe and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the learned Phiſition.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9025:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
